好的，嗯，是的，谢谢大家的到来。我们开始吧。
Okay, uh, yeah, thanks for coming. Let's get started.
好的，希望你们喜欢PA一。
Okay, so hope you enjoyed PA one.
是的，PA二会在今晚午夜前发布。
Yeah. So pA two will be released by midnight tonight.
我们已经听取了你们的反馈。
And we heard your feedback.
所以我们会减少PA二的工作量，但内容会更深入。
So we are going to reduce workload in p two, but it's going to be deeper.
这意味着如果你真的想做得很好，你可以在PA二上花更多时间。
Which means that if you want to really do pretty well, you can spend more time on pA two.
是的。但你也可以选择不这么做，因为我们所有的问题设计都是为了让你能够
Yeah. But you can also choose not to because we all design question in a way where you are able to
优化你的算法并获得更多分数。
optimize your algorithm and get more grades.
好吗？因为内容会更深入，所以我们会允许你们合作。
Okay? Because it's going to be deeper, so we will allow you to collaborate.
你们可以尝试组建最多三人的小组，一起讨论如何完成。
You can try to form a team with up to three members, and you guys can discuss how
为了写出更好的代码，你们将能够进行合作。
to write a better version of the code, you'll be able to collaborate.
当你们提交PA二时，所有人都需要标明自己的合作者是谁。
And when you submit PA two, you all need to mark who are your collaborators,
IP三我们会让它非常轻量化，和PA一、PA二相比，几乎没有什么代码量。
IP three, we are going to make it pretty lightweight, very few coding compared to PA one and PA two.
我们会在PS三中给你们一些非常有趣的问题。
And we are going to give you some very fun question in ps three,
你们将能够理解sync value中发生了什么。
you'll be able to understand what is going on in sync value.
这是我在这门课程中一直强调的一个重要主题。
That's one major topic I have been always talking about in this course.
好的，今天我想完成凝聚部分的内容。
Yeah. Cool. Okay. Today, I want to finish the condensation part
因为我觉得在上一次讲座中，我们讲了线性凝聚。
because I think in my previous lecture, we talk about linear condadonTday,
今天我想把那部分讲完。
I want to finish that part.
然后我需要介绍一个非常重要的内容，就像我说的，可能你们需要记住它。
Then I need to introduce a very important thing that like I said, probably you need to memorize
那部分是混合精度，因为混合精度是最适应的技术之一。
that part that is mixed precision, because mixed precision is one of
混合精度是目前最具适应性的技术之一，对吧？
the most adaptive techniques from contaation, okay?
然后我们将开始下一个重要章节，就是并行化。
And then we will start our next big chapter, which is paralyzation.
好的。好的。我们来回顾一下，对吧？
Okay. Okay. Just to recap, right?
上一节课，我们从浮点数的表示和浮点运算讲起。
Last lecture, we starting from the floating point orientation and the floating point arithmetics.
然后我们开始讨论如何对浮点数进行量化。
And we start talking about how to quantize floating points into.
第一个方法是基于K均值的压缩，这样我们可以减少存储空间，
The first one is key means based condensation, where we are able to reduce storage,
但我们无法节省计算量，对吧。
but we are not able to save compute, right.
我们还介绍了一种更常见、更通用的编码方法，
And we also introduce a more common more general codoon method,
线性压缩，可以将精度从浮点数降低到整数。
linear condensation, where we'll be able to reduce the precision from floating point to integer.
我们其实也可以把计算从浮点运算迁移到
And we can also basically migrate the computation from floating point arithmetic into
比如整数或者目标精度的运算，这样也能节省计算资源，对吧？
say integer or target precision arithmetic, which we also save to compute, okay?
我觉得当我们谈论这种压缩，尤其是在接近的情况下，
I think when we talk about this condensation, especially in the near condition,
我们总是假设第一种方式，对吧？
we always assume the first one, right?
这里我给出一个例子，就是每个张量的压缩。
Here I give the lime, that is per tensor condensation.
也就是说，给我一个张量。
That is give me a tensor.
我会对张量里的所有元素、所有条目应用同样的压缩方式，对吧？
I'm going to apply the same condensation, right, for all the elements, all the entries in a tensor.
但实际上，这种方式并不总是效果很好，对吧？
But in practice, this does not always work well, okay?
所以有时候我们可能需要更细粒度的压缩方式，这会带来
So sometimes we probably need more fun green condensation granularity, and this will bring us
更常用的分块技术，或者说量化方案。
to more common use cotton technique, or I would say quantitation scheme,
也就是每通道量化和分组量化。
which is per channel condensation and group condensation.
好的。我今天的RM有很多内容，
Okay. I many today's RM,
我认为大家基本上都会做，比如分组量化或者潜在量化。
I think people basically do, for example, group condition or poteno coddation.
我接下来会介绍它们是什么。
I'm going to introduce what they.
在那之前，我们先回顾一下潜在量化。
Before that, let's revisit potential condition.
如果你还记得这个线性量化，我们需要确定，这里是一个实数，
If you remember this linear condition, we need to determine so here is the real number,
比如说浮点数，而Q是量化后的数值。
for example, flowing point number and the Q is quantized number.
如果我们想要应用线性量化，我们需要确定两个关键参数，
And if we want to apply linear codiation, we need to figure out two key parameters,
就是缩放因子S和零点Z。
which is the scale S, and the Z zero point.
通常情况下，我们会先确定Z，也就是零点，对吧？
Normally, we decide the Z are zero, right?
所以基本上我们有一个参数叫做皮肤因子，对吧？
So basically we have one parameter that is skinning factor, okay?
给定这个张量，我们要做的基本上是找出
And given this tensor, what we do is basically we figure
在原始域的浮点数中，呃，QMAX 和 Q 分别是多少？
out in the floating point in the original domain, uh, so what is QMAX and Q?
RMAX 是多少？Rmin 又是多少，对吧？
What is the RMAX? What is the Rmin, right?
然后我们像这样计算皮肤因子。对，没错。
And then we calculate the skin factor like this. Right. Okay.
很简单，对吧？但实际上，这并不总是有效，就像我说的那样。
Pretty simple. Okay. But in reality, this does not always work, like I said.
这是一个真实的例子，我要做矩阵乘法。
So this is the real example where I'm going to do uh matrix multiplication.
嗯，我有一个权重矩阵，记作 W，W 有不同的通道，是多维的，对吧？
Um, so I have the weight matrix which is W and W has different channels it's multi dimensional, ok?
如果你画出每个通道的值，并试图把它们投影到这个图上，
And if you draw the uh values of, uh, each channel and try to project it into this graph,
你会发现有几个通道的动态范围非常大，对吧？
you see, there are a few channels that have a very large dynamic range, right?
但大多数通道基本上都保持在零附近的一个小范围内。
But most of the channels they just basically stay within a small range around zero.
但你可以看到，有一些通道会上下波动，对吧，非常剧烈。
But you can see, there are a few channels that goes up and down, right, very drastically.
如果我们用单一的缩放因子a来做量化，会有什么问题？
And uh and if we use single scale a to do quantdation, what's the problem?
基本上，当我们计算那个S时，问题在于S会
So basically, when we calculate that S, the problem is the S will
适应那些具有大动态范围的数字，对吧？
adapt to those large dynamic range numbers, right?
然后我们就会丢失那些小数字的精度，对吧？
And we all lose precision for those small numbers, right?
所以常见的情况是，当我们用单一的S时，
So a common there is that when we use single S,
会被那些异常值权重强烈影响。
we'll be strongly influenced by those outlier weights.
比如，在这个图中，你可以看到有不少层的权重非常大或者很大，
For example, in this figure, you see quite a few layer weights, very large or large,
是正的或者是负的。
positive or are negative.
好吗？解决方案其实很直接。
Okay? And the solution is basically we try to it's very straightforward.
当你看到这个问题时，我们想出的方案就是对每个通道都做antradt，
When you see this, you come up with a solution that we basically do antradt for
这样就能解决我们的问题，对吧？那我们该怎么做呢？
each channel that will solve our problem, okay? So how do we do that?
这里我要比较一下pertensor conuation和perteno conation。
So here I'm going to compare pertensor conuation and perteno conation.
给定这个矩阵，好吗？
So given that matrix, okay.
假设我们基本上做同样的事情，至少是两位的condensation。
Let's assume we basically do the same thing, at least two bit condensation.
如果我们做pretensor connation，我们基本上需要计算RMX，这里我
So if we do pretensor connation, we basically need to figure out the RMX Here I
稍微简化了一下，假设零点对齐，也就是说这个值等于零。
simply about a little bit by assuming zero point is aligned, which means this is equal to zero.
然后我们算出RMX是2.12。
And then we figure out RMX is 2.12.
然后我们用这个公式，得到skin向量。
And we basically do this equation, right, and we get the skin vector.
然后我们用线性条件方程应用这个蒙皮因子，
And we apply this skinning factor using our linear conduon equation,
我们基本上得到了接触权重，对吧？
we basically get the contact weight, okay?
我们可以用量化权重来重建原始权重，然后我们会得到矩阵。
And we can use quantat weight to reconstruct the original weight, and we'll get the matrix.
好吧？这其实很简单。
Okay? This is pretty easy.
那如果我们对每个通道做连接呢？
So what if we do per channel connation?
如果我们对每个通道做编码，那我们就有更多的灵活性，对吧？
So if we do per channel codation then we have more flexibility. Okay?
所以对于每个通道，我们会观察那里的矩阵，并尝试找出
So for each channel, we are going to observe the matrix there and we try to figure out a
一个特定的蒙皮因子。
specific skinning factor for it.
好的，这里每一行都是一个通道。
Okay? So here, each row is a channel.
所以我们要做的基本上是，嗯，对于第一行，第一个通道，
So what we do is basically Um, for the first row, first channel,
我们算出最大值等于2.09，然后我们可以计算第一行的蒙皮权重，
we figure out the MAX equal to 2.09, and we can calculate the first row skinning actor,
也就是木材，然后我们继续这样做，对吧？
which is the lumber, and we continue doing so, right?
所以我们现在需要维护四个蒙皮向量。
So we need to maintain four skinning vectors now.
好吗？记住，屏幕因子是浮点型的木材。
Okay? Remember, screen factor is floating point lumber.
好的，这意味着我们实际上需要多花一点存储空间来存储更多的蒙皮权重，好吗？
Okay. That means we actually spend a little bit more storage to store more skinning actors, okay?
但好消息是，如果我们这样做，我们可以对每个通道应用这个蒙皮向量，
But the good news is, if we do this, we can apply this skinning vector per channel,
然后我们会得到一个新的权重范围，并且我们可以重建它，好吗？
and we'll get a new contest width, and we can reconstruct it, okay?
在这里我们基本上可以比较，呃，基本上是重建后的权重，呃，
And here we can basically compare the um, basically the reconstructed weight, uh,
和原始权重进行比较，我们可以尝试量化，尝试衡量重建误差。
versus the original weight we can try to quantize the try to measure the reconstruction arrow.
所以在左边部分，我们基本上得到了量化误差，大约是2点，呃，28。
So in the left part, we basically get the quantity arrow which is two point uh 28.
在这一部分，我们可以做得更好一点。
And in the part, we can do a little bit better.
好吗？这基本上就是给大家一个直观的理解。
Okay? That basically give intuition.
如果我们做更多有趣的高级量化，我们会减少量化误差。
If we do more fun grand uh conduation we are going to reduce coening error.
这意味着这会反映在模型的准确率上，对吧，
Which means that this will be reflected in the model accuracy, right,
因为你们都会有更高一点的精度或者动态范围。
because you all have a little bit more precision or dynamic range.
所以你的模型表现会比，比如说只做普通量化，要好一点。
So your model will perform a little bit better than, for example, doing potential condation.
好吗？但代价是你要保存更多的S，对吧？
Okay? But at the cost of saving more S, right?
因为每个S都是浮点数，S其实比两位整数要重得多。
So S is actually pretty heavy compared to two bit integer because each S is a floating point.
而且为了表示一个浮点数，
And in order to represent a floating point,
我觉得你至少需要用LP8或者LP16，好吗？
I think you at least need LP eight or LP 16, okay?
很好，这个想法非常直接，我认为人们在今天的机器学习模型中经常应用它。
Cool. So this is very straightforward idea, and, um, I think people apply this
这种方法在当今的机器模型中被广泛应用。
a lot in today's machinery models.
很明显，如果我们想做得更好，那基本上就是分组凝聚，对吧？
And apparently, uh, if we want to do even better that is basically group connation, right?
我可以做越来越细致的凝聚，这样基本上就得到了分组凝聚。
I can do more and more finer green, um, condensation, and I will o basically get group condensation.
比如说，我可以尝试检查这个矩阵中的数值，
For example, I can basically try to inspect the values in this matrix and
我试图找出那些数值接近的元素。
I try to figure out those values that are close.
然后我为那些数值范围接近的一组元素应用一个缩放向量。
And I basically apply a skin vector for that group of values which are close in range.
接着我再找出另一组元素，然后计算另一个缩放因子，对吧？
And then I figure out another group and I calculate another scale, right?
这意味着我正在做细粒度的凝聚，好吗？
That means that I'm doing fine green condensation, okay?
这样做的优点就是我们可以获得更高的精度，因为如果你对每个元素都进行凝聚的话
So the prose is basically we have more accuracy because if you do per element codation
你其实什么都没做，对吧？
you are essentially doing nothing, right?
是的，你基本上没有进行量化。
Yeah, you are basically doing no conduation.
好的。如果你用百分比量化，基本上就是用一个刻度来表示所有的数值。
Okay. And if you do percentage quantity, basically you use one scale for all the values.
好处是，如果你更偏向绿色（环保），那你基本上会有更高的精度。
Okay. The pros is if you are more fun green, then you are basically doing more accuracy.
你的误差会更小。
You have less duty error.
明白了吗？但缺点是，如果你对每个数值分别处理，就像我说的，你其实没有做量化，
Okay? But the counts is if you do per value, like I said, you are not doing dutation,
那你就会回到使用浮点数表示和浮点数运算，
then you are rolling back to use the flowing point orientation and the flowing point arithmetic,
这样其实你什么都没有节省，对吧？
you are saving nothing, right?
所以最终你会面临一个问题，那就是
So basically, eventually you are facing a problem that is what is what is
你到底想在这里做怎样的量化粒度？
the quantuation granularity you want to do here?
是的，H，所以看起来我们有了一个通道。
Yeah. H, so it seems like we got a channel.
我们得到了一个非常高精度和折扣。
We got a fing high precision and discounting.
就是这样。
That is Yeah.
是的，你可以这么做。好的，酷。这有点极端，因为就像我说的，
Yeah, you can do that. Yeah. Okay. Cool. This is a little bit extreme because like I said,
这很复杂，因为真的取决于你怎么看，
it's very complicated because it really depends on how you looking like,
更实际的方法基本上是做两级凝聚。
more practical way is basically do two level condensation.
这里，最初我们有时间量化权重减去零点，对吧？
Here, originally, we have time quantize weight minus zero point, okay?
我们可以做的是只做两级，好吗？
What we can do is we just two level, okay?
所以在这个矩阵里，你可以看到，我们在做，呃，缺失修改
So in this matrix, you can see, we are doing, uh, the miss modification
然后我们得到了右侧的结果。
and we get the results on the right hand side.
所以我们可以做两级处理。
So we can do two level.
第一级是我们在这里应用全局凝聚因子Gamma，
The first level is we apply global condensation factor Gamma here,
这个因子会应用在张量之前，好吗？
which will be applied pretensor, okay?
然后在此基础上，我们继续对其进行量化。
And then on top of that, we continue to quantize it.
但在第一级条件下，我们将其量化为更低的自由位数，比如16位到8位。
But in the first level condition we quantize it to lower bit of freedom 16-8 bit.
然后在第一级，我们将其从八位进一步压缩到比如说四位整数。
And then at the first level, we contact it from eight bit two to say four bit integer.
好吗？我们这样做分层凝聚。好的。
Okay? We do this hierarchical condadation. Okay.
如果我们用方程来表示，其实我们就是从量子态转变为方程。
So if we represent this as equation is basically we are basically changing from quit to equation.
这里我们有两个缩放因子。
Here we have two skinning factor.
好的，我们首先用一个通用的缩放因子gamma对张量中的所有元素进行缩放，
Okay. We first scale all elements in the tensor using a common skinning factor gamma,
然后我们是每组一个技能，对吧，SQ。
and then we skill per group, yeah, SQ.
这样做更好的原因是我们节省了很多存储空间。
So the reason this is better is because we save a lot of storage.
所以我们不需要为每组做一个皮肤因子。
So we don't have to, like, do one skinning factor per group.
至少在更高精度下，我们不需要这样做，对吧？
Um, at least a higher precision, we don't need to do that, okay?
就像我说的，这里的Gamma是一个浮点型的跨绿色皮肤因子，
Here, like I said, the Gamma is a floating point cross green skinning factor and
SQ是每个向量的整数技能因子。
SQ is an integer per vector skill factor.
我们只需要为橙色准备一份Gamma，但每组需要很多不同的SQ。
We only need one copy of Gamma for oranges, but we need many many different SQ for each group.
假设我们正在做四比特量化。
Assume that we are doing four bit quantization.
也就是说我们的最终目标是四比特，而我们原始的权重
That is our inventual target is four bit, and our original basically our original weight
基本上是浮点型的，我们正在做这种全局压缩。
is basically floating point, we are doing this global condensation.
我们正在做的分组条件是每个向量技能每16个元素用4位。
We are doing group condition is four bit per vector skill every 16 elements.
成本基本上是4加。
The cost is essentially four plus.
164加4，然后在16个数字之间摊销，对吧？
164 plus four, then amort has across 16 numbers, right?
因为每组有16个元素，对吗？
Because each group has 16 elements, okay?
所以我们实际上是用4.25位有效地表示每个数字。
Therefore, we are essentially effectively well represented each number using 4.25 bits.
明白了吗？这基本上就是当你读一些论文时，有些人会说，
Okay? That is basically when you read some papers, some people say,
嗯，我基本上是用4.5位来量化我的权重。
um, I'm basically quantizing my weight using uh four point half bits.
这就是这个说法的来源，明白了吗？
That's where it's coming from. Okay?
他们基本上是在做这种分层压缩。
They are basically doing this kind of hierarchical condensation.
并且有一个缩放因子是在不同元素之间摊销的。
And there is one skinning factor which is amortized across different elements.
所以平均来说，你基本上每个条目做了4点，嗯，4又四分之一比特的压缩。
And so in average, you are basically doing four point,
好吗？如果你真的非常想要再精细一点，你可以做得更激进一点。
uh, four and a quarter bit condensation, per entry.
你知道，可以采用更激进的权重方式。
Okay? And if you really, really, want to grind this a little bit, okay, you can do like,
至少，你可以做多层次的分层压缩。
you know, more like aggressive weight.
好吗？你只需要不断减少你的分组集合。
At least, you do multi level hierarchical condensation.
在较小的分组中，你会用更低的比特数，在较大的分组中，比如说，
Okay? You just continue to reduce your group set.
在张量级别，你会用更高的比特数。
And at a smaller group, you are going to use a lower bit, and at a larger group, for example,
这样我可以给你更高的精度，但实现起来会更复杂。
at the tensor level, you are going to use a higher bit.
好的，明白。那这个部分有问题吗？
And I can give you a lot of accuracy, but it's more complicated.
好的。嗯，酷。大家有问题吗？
Okay. Yeah. Okay. Cool. Any questions on this?
基本上，这就是实际操作中凹陷的样子。
So basically, this is how denting looks like in practice.
那么，当你开始在这个区域工作时，
So, um, so when you start working on this area,
我认为，你真的需要关注一下你的权重的数值。
I think, you really want to look into the values of your weight.
比如说，你拿到一个模型。
For example, you are given a model.
你基本上想要绘制一下你的模型权重分布，比如说，
You want to basically plot your model width distribution, for example,
按通道或者沿着某个维度，然后你试图观察
per channel or basically along some dimension, and you try to see the distribution of
这些权重的分布，并尝试找出一个合适的量化策略，对吧？
these weights and try to figure out what's the right strategy for a perform quandon. Okay.
好，我们一直在讨论如何对权重量化，但是你知道，在深度学习工作中，
Okay, we have been talking about how to quantize the weights, but, you know, in deepen work,
我们还有另一个需要担心的事情，就是内存密集型的激活。
we have another worry, uh like memory intensive thing, which is activation.
有时候我们也需要对激活进行量化，对吧？
We also need to quantize our activation sometimes, okay?
那么，如何对激活值进行量化呢。
So how to quantize activation.
激活的问题在于，权重，尤其是在推理阶段是静态的。
So the problem of activation is, weight, especially inference time is static.
在训练阶段，我认为它是半静态的，因为，
At the training time, I think is semi static because,
尤其是当你的模型即将收敛时，
especially when your model is going to converge,
你的权重只会有很小的变化，嗯，更新。
you only have a small Delta updated, um, to your weight.
所以你的权重基本上会在一个很小的范围内波动。
So your weight will basically escalate among small range.
我会说它是半静态的。
I would say it's semi static.
但对于激活来说就很不一样了，对吧，因为每次你输入一个
But for activity it's quite different, right, because every time you are giving a batch of
批次的数据进行推理或训练时，每个批次的数据可能都非常不同。
data in inference or in training, and the batch of data could be very different across batches.
所以每次你给网络输入一个批次时，激活值的变化可能会很大，对吧。
So every time when you give a batch network, the activation value can change a lot, right.
这意味着对于每一组激活值，你都需要确定正确的army和RMAX。
So which means that for every group of activation, you have to determine the right army and RMAX.
而对于不同的批次，这个army和MAX可能会非常不同。
And for different batches, this army and MAX can be very different.
这就是为什么当我们尝试对激活值进行量化时，需要使用一种叫做动态范围调整的技巧。
That's why when we try to quantize activations, we need to apply a trick called dynamic ranging.
所以我们需要为每个数据点动态地确定army和RMAX。
So we need to dynamically determine army and RMAX for each data point.
明白了吗？确定激活值的army和RMAX有两种方法。
Okay? So there are two ways to determine army and RMAxu for activations.
第一种方法非常简单。
The first way is very simple.
我们基本上就是做移动平均，好吗？
We basically do moving average, okay?
也就是说，每当我们观察到一个批次时，我们会用Apha来控制，
So that is every time we observe a batch, we basically using Apha to control,
我们想从这个批次中学习多少，好吗？
how much we want to learn from this batch, okay?
我们用这个offa来让我们的Army Max稍微向当前批次靠近一点，好吗？
We use this offa to slightly move our Army Max toward the current batch, okay?
通过这样做，我认为我们可以适应那些非常特殊的新批次。
And by doing this, I think we can adapt to new badges which are extremely say,
它们有不同的动态范围，对吧？
have a different dynamic range, okay?
另一种方法是，你了解你的数据。假设你了解你的数据。
Okay, another way is that, you know your data. Assume you know your data.
例如，你在某个模型上训练了你的数据，并且你知道，
For example, you train your data on some model and you know that say,
我要在自动驾驶环境中部署我的数据，而且我知道，
I'm going to deploy my data, um, in autous driving environment, and I know uh,
我要读取的大多数自动驾驶危机中的图像或视频都来自圣地亚哥。
most of the images or videos I'm going to read in auto driving crises from San Diego.
所以，这意味着你实际上知道你的数据分布，对吧？
So, um, then that means that you actually know your distribution data, right?
那你可以收集一个数据集，这个数据集叫做校准数据集，对吧？
So you can connect a dataset, which is called a calibration dataset, okay?
在你部署模型之前，你首先在校准数据集上运行你的量化过程，
And before you deploy your model, you first run your condensation on the calibration data set
并找出这个数据集可能的最小值和最大值。
and figure out what would be the possible army and RMAX for that dataset.
你可以假设在测试时检查推理时，
And you can assume that at the test time inspect the inference,
你的数据不会有太大的变化。
your data is not going to shift a lot.
所以这个army和RMAx应该为后续批次和新数据保留，好吗？
So this army and RMAx should preserve for incoming batches, new data, okay?
这基本上就是我们在实际中使用的技巧。
And this is basically the trick we use in practice.
所以在很多Ms中，当你尝试量化模型时，你必须确定你的目标领域。
So in many Ms, when you try to quantize the model, you have to figure out your target domain.
例如，你希望M执行一个特定任务，比如生成代码或做聊天机器人。
For example, you want M to do see a specific task that generates code or doing chatbard.
如果这是你的任务场景，你基本上会收集一些聊天机器人数据，然后尝试校准
If that's your tax case you basically connect some chatboard data and you try to calibrate
一下Arman RMAx，然后你用
a little bit the Arman RMAx and you quantat using
校准后的rmi RMAx来量化，这样效果应该会很好。
the calibrated rmi RMAx and that should work pretty well.
好吗？这就是我们所说的条件下的校准。
Okay? So this is what we call calibration in condition.
我认为这是一个非常重要的步骤，可以确保你的模型确实，
I think this is a very essential procedure to make sure your model indeed, uh,
对这类异常值，对不起，异常激活具有鲁棒性，对吧？
robust to those kind of outliers sorry, outlier activations, okay?
很好，这里有问题吗？
Cool. Any question here?
好的，关于量化就讲到这里。
Okay, that's all about quantitation.
我认为这是一个非常重要的领域。
I think this is a very important area.
嗯，我接下来会多讲一点关于这个话题，
Um, I'm going to talk a little bit more about this,
但在那之前，我们先来聊一下混合精度，好吗？
but before that, let's talk about mixed precision, okay.
所以我认为现在有了量化的知识，你可能已经知道
So I think now with the knowledge of connotation, you probably already know
混合精度要做什么了，对吧？
what mixed press is going to do, right?
也就是说，对于目标领域，
That is, for the target domain,
我不会限制自己只用某一个特定的比特数。
I'm not going to restrict myself to be one specific uh, number of bits.
我不会只针对四位或者八位比特。
I'm not going to target only four bits or eight bits.
我基本上可以混合使用所有这些可能性。
I can basically mix all this kind of possibility.
我会尝试找出一个最佳平衡点，让我尽可能多地节省资源。
And I try to figure out a sweet spot where I can save as much as possible.
同时还能保持相对较好的准确率，好吗？
Well, I still have relatively good accuracy, okay?
为了让大家更有动力，其实在我们之前的课程中，我们说过每一层，
So to motivate a little bit, basically, my in our previous lecture, we said that each layer,
我们会对权重或激活使用相同的目标比特数。
we are going to apply the same, uh, target number bits for, uh, either with or activation.
这被称为统一量化。
This is called uniform connotation.
但是我们可以更聪明一点，对吧？
Okay. But we can be a little bit smarter, right?
所以，我们可以采用一种非统一量化方式，这被称为混合精度量化。
So, we can do a long uniform condui which is called a mixed precision condition.
好的。那么对于每一层，呃，
Okay. So for each layer, uh,
我基本上可以针对权重和激活，选择不同的比特数，
I can basically target different number of bits, uh, for weights and activation,
因为背后的直觉是每一层都有不同的动态范围，
because the intuition behind this is each layer has a different dynamic range and
以及对精度有不同程度的鲁棒性。
different kind of robustness to precision.
也许对于那一层，它不是那么敏感，所以我可以更激进地应用量化。
Maybe for that layer, it's not so sensitive, so I can more aggressively apply codaon.
但对于那一层，呃，它非常，呃，敏感，你实际上不能
But for that layer, uh, it's very, uh, like, uh, sensitive and you cannot actually
修改任何微小的数值，所以你必须保留原始精度。
modify any small amount of value, so you have to preserve the original precision.
明白吗？我基本上可以找出每一层应该用什么样的精度，
Okay? And I can basically figure out what is the right precision I use for each layer,
至少在粒度上可以做到。
uh, at least granularity.
但这种方法的问题是，呃，它太复杂了，对吧，
But the problem of this approach is u it's too complicated, right,
因为神经网络有很多层，你真的需要
because a neural network has so many layers, and you really need
做大量的工作来确定每一层的激活值和权重应该用什么精度，对吧？
to do a lot of work to figure out what is the right precision I use for
每一层的激活值、权重都要考虑合适的精度，好吗？
activations for weight and for each layer, okay?
那么该怎么做呢？在我们弄清楚怎么做之前，
So how to do this? So, uh, before we figure out how to do this,
我可以先给你展示一下它的复杂性。
um, uh, I can show you the complexity.
基本上，对于每一层来说，比如我们的目标位数、预算是八位，对吧？
So basically, for each layer, say, our target bits is our budget is eight bits, okay?
那么对于每一层的权重或激活值，你基本上有64种选择，对吗？
Then for each layer for the weight or for activation, you basically have 64 choices, right?
而且你有很多很多层。
And you have the many layers and layers.
所以你有一个64次方的设计空间，非常庞大。
So basically, you have a design space which is 64 power, okay, which is super huge.
对于这种问题，我认为学术界……
And and this is very, um, for this kind of problem, I think academia,
人们真的很喜欢这样，因为你有项目可以申请，对吧？
people really like that because you have something to grant, okay?
当你想出一个新方案时，你就可以发表新论文，对吧？
You can publish new papers when you figure out a new scheme, right?
所以，嗯，有一种方法可以解决这个问题，基本上就是你用，
So, um, one way to figure out this is basically you use,
就像我说的，机器学习用于系统，好吗？
like I said, machine learning four systems, okay?
我想我在兼容性课程里讲过这个，对吧。
I think I talked about this in compatible class, right.
在C时代的课程里，你要优化这些循环，对吧？
C era class you are going to optimize those loops, right?
你有很多很多方法可以展开这些循环。
You have many many ways to enroll these loops.
如果你让人来做这个，会花很多时间。
So if you ask human to do that, it will take a lot of time.
所以你其实也可以找到一些机器学习模型，然后你尝试
So you can also basically find some machine learning models and you try to
基本上执行一些引导式搜索，并用代价模型来引导搜索。
basically perform some guided search and use a cost model to guide search.
这张幻灯片表达的是同样的想法，对吧？
So this slide is the same idea, okay?
我在做准确的评估。
I'm doing accurate critique.
明白吗？每次我都会列举一种可能性，把某些条件位应用到
Okay? Every time I'm going to enumerate a possibility that apply certain bits of
每一层的宽度和激活上。
condition to the width and activation of each layer.
然后我应用它，看看我的准确率是多少，
And I then apply it and I try to see how many accuracy I have and
还会看我能节省多少内存或计算资源。
also how many memory or computer I can save.
基本上，我有一个代价函数。
Basically, I have a cost function.
然后我测量实际的代价，尝试拟合这种“演员-评论家”循环，
And then I measure the real cost and I try to fit this kind of actor critical loop
并试图学习一个能够建模比特数与最终代价关系的模型。
and try to learn some model that can model this relation between lumber bits and the eventual cost.
然后我基本上就可以这样做了。
And then I can basically do this.
我基本上可以把它部署在一台电脑上，让它运行七天，然后返回
I can basically deploy this on a computer and let it run for seven days and return
一个很好的发现结果。
a good solution in the discovery.
明白吗？事实证明，这个方法非常有效。
Okay? And it turns out that this is pretty effective.
如果你把我刚才描述的这个HAQ方法和均匀量化方法进行比较的话，
If you compare this HAQ which is a method that I just described compared to uniform codenation, uh,
你可以看到它确实能够找到一个很好的方案，
you can see it can indeed figure out pretty good and scheme where you can
可以在保持准确率的同时，依然拥有不错的延迟表现。
preserve accuracy where still have a pretty good latency.
好的，好的。这非常有趣，是一个非常好的研究领域，
Okay. Okay. This is very interesting, very good research field,
我认为在这个领域有很多人发表了论文。
and I think people publish a lot in this.
接下来我要介绍的是，这篇论文？
But next what I'm going to introduce is, This paper?
这篇论文没有放在阅读清单里，但我强烈推荐，好吗？
This paper is not put on the reading list, but I highly recommend, okay?
这是由英伟达撰写的一篇混合精度训练论文。
This is a mixed precision training paper written by media.
不知为何，这篇论文如今成了标准，好吗？
And for some reason, this paper becomes the standard today, okay?
顺便说一下，这个混合精度训练正是我刚才描述的内容。
Um, By the way, this mixed preceding training is exactly what I described.
所以你基本上会在你的新网络中，对不同的算子或层应用不同的精度。
So you basically apply different precision for different operators layers in your new network.
但不幸的是，这种方案并不是由自动化框架发现的。
But unfortunately, uh, this scheme is not discovered by automatic framework.
这同样是由英伟达的专家设计的。
Okay, it's again, designed by expert from media.
所以我认为，英伟达的人花了很多时间去研究
So basically, I think media people, they spend a lot of time on figuring
如何在双网络中正确地组合不同位数，
out what is the right way of combining different bits, um, in Twin Networks
他们最终发表了这篇论文，而这篇论文也成为了
and they eventually publish this paper, and this paper becomes the standard
训练语言模型的标准。
in train language models.
好吗？所以我想花点时间深入讲解这篇论文，我希望你们真的
Okay? So I want to spend some time diving into this paper, and I want to make sure you guys really
明白这里在做什么，好吗？
understand what is doing here, okay?
直觉上，在许多神经网络中，尤其是语言模型里，
So the intuition is, in many, many neural networks, especially in language models.
层对动态范围和精度更加敏感。
Okay? So layers are more sensitive to dynamic range and precision.
我今天之所以提到这个，是因为你们已经完成了P1，对吧。
The reason I brought up this today is because you already finished P one, right.
我觉得你们中有些人可能在softmax这里卡住了，对吗？
And I think some of you probably got stuck on softmax, right?
当你做softmax的时候，你已经返回了很多很大的数值，对吧。
When you do softmax, you already return, a lot of lumber value, right.
这是因为在很多操作，比如softmax中，
So that is because for many, many operations like softmax, um, where you are
你基本上都会涉及到这种操作，归一化。
basically involved with this kind of operation, normalization.
你会得到一个浮点数值，呃，你会得到很多浮点数值，然后你会得到
You take a floating point value, uh you take many floating point value and you get
一个是数值的求和，然后你要对它进行归一化，对吧？
a summion of the values and then you normalize it, okay?
对于这种操作来说，它对精度非常敏感。
For this kind of operation, it's very sensitive to precision.
好的。如果你使用较低位数的精度，你会损失很多准确性，明白吗？
Okay. If you use a lower bit precision, you are going to lose a lot of accuracy, okay?
所以直觉上，当我们尝试计算这种归一化操作时，
So intuition is when we try to calculate this kind of normalization operation,
我们需要非常非常精确。
we need to be very, very precise.
呃，精确基本上意味着你需要为小数部分分配更多的位数，
Uh, Being precise basically means that you need to allocate more bits for fraction,
对吧，如果你还记得我们的课程内容。
right, if you remember our lecture, okay?
同样地，这也是Softmax的一部分，对吧？
And similarly, uh, this is part of Softmax, right?
记住在softmax中，你也要用到指数函数，对吧？
And remember in softmax, you also are taking expansion function, right?
所以基本上是e的某个数的幂。
So basically E Samsung number.
这个数值很容易就会爆炸，对吧？
And this number can easily get explode, right?
因为它是以E为底的幂，对吧？
Because it's a power of E, right?
如果某个数真的要爆炸了，我们该怎么办？
And if something really is going to explode, then what should we do?
加一个动态范围，对吧。
Add a dynamic range, right.
好，那我们怎么加动态范围呢？
Okay, so how do add a dynamic range?
让它更容易爆炸，对吧？
Give it more explod, right?
也就是在爆炸的部分分配更多的比特位。
That is allocate more bits on the exploding part.
这意味着softmax是一个非常神奇的操作，
Which means that softmax is such a magical operation that
它对动态范围和精度都很敏感。
is sensitive to dynamic range and sensitive to precision.
明白了吗？这就是直觉。
Okay? And this is intuition.
所以当你执行softmax时，你可能需要为指数和小数部分分配更多的位数
So when you perform softmax, you probably should allocate more bits
对吧？
on both explent and fraction, right?
这意味着我们其实没有选择的余地。
That means that we really don't have a choice.
我们必须为softmax使用更高精度的浮点数。
We have to use a higher precision floating point for softmax.
好的。同样地，对于这种梯度累加，
Okay. And similarly, for this kind of grading accumulation,
你总是把梯度加到参数上，对吧？
you always add grading to the parameters, right?
有时候你的梯度可能会非常大，对吧，尤其是在训练初期
And sometimes your grading could be extremely large, right, especially at the initial training
或者当你现在遇到这种情况时，你该怎么办？
or when you're now, what do you do?
它对动态范围非常敏感，所以你要确保在累加时，
It's very sensitive to dynamic range, so you want to make sure that when you accumulate,
不要让你的浮点位数溢出，明白吗？
you don't explode your rolling point bits, okay?
基于这种直觉，我刚才展示的那篇论文，基本上提出了一个方案。
So with this kind of intuition, so the paper I just showed, they basically come up with a scheme.
他们认为我们应该识别那些对
They are saying that we should identify those ops that are extremely sensitive
动态范围精度极其敏感的操作。
to precision in dynamic range.
然后我们应该对这些操作使用全精度，比如说，
And then we should use full precision, for example,
例如1.32，只要遇到这些操作就用全精度。
1.32 for them, whenever we met these kind of ops.
但一旦完成这些操作，我们基本上就可以降到更低的精度，因为我们总是希望
But once we finish these ops, we can basically downcast to lower precision because we always want to
总是希望使用更低的精度，对吧。
know always want to use lower precision, right.
更低的精度在内存和计算上都更高效，对吧？
Lower precision is more memory efficient and more computer efficient, okay?
基于这种直觉，他们开始做了很多实验。
And with this kind of intuition, they start doing a lot of experiments, okay.
他们试图找出如何正确地组合不同的精度。
They try to figure out what is the right way to combine different precisions.
于是他们想出了这个方案。
And they come up with this scheme.
好的。我让你看这个30秒，然后我们再详细讲解。
Okay. I'll like you look at this for 30 seconds then we go through it in detail.
这是我从那篇论文中引用的一个图。
Okay, so this is a figure I quoted from that paper.
如果你想了解更多细节，可以去读那篇论文，但我们现在来过一遍，好吗？
And if you want to know more detail, go read that paper, but let's go through this, okay?
这基本上就是现在混合精度的工作方式。
So this is basically how mixed precision works today.
它是混合了两种精度。
It's mixing two precisions.
一种是浮点32位。
One is the floating 0.32.
另一种是浮点16位。
The other is flowing 0.16.
这是直到上个月为止的标准。
Okay. And this is the standard today until last month.
好吗？因为上个月，
Okay? Because last month,
我记得Deep Sik对吧，他们发布了一篇论文说他们所有操作都在AP八上完成。
I think deep sik right, they release a paper saying that they do everything in AP eight.
好的，那我觉得还是可以提一下这个，但我会稍后再提Deep Sik。
Okay. Uh, so I think it's still good to bring up this, but I'm going to bring up Deep sick later.
好的，他们是怎么做Peight的。
Okay, how they do Peight.
但这其实还是像CheBT，像现在大多数模型的训练方式一样。
But this is still like how CheBT how most of, like, today's model are trained, okay.
所以这里可以看到，
So here it is seen that,
我有一个主权重。
I have a master weight.
这个主权重基本上是以浮点0.32保存的。
Okay. This master weight was basically saved in floating 0.32.
好的，非常高的精度，非常高的精度。
Okay, high precision, very high precision.
好的，每当我开始做计算时，我首先会做一次降精度操作。
Okay. And whenever I try to start doing competition, what I do is I'm going to first do a downcast.
对吧？这就是过程。
Okay? This is the dution right.
所以基本上，我是在做32位到16位的降精度处理。
So basically, I'm downcasting 32-16 bit.
好的。我基本上得到了浮点0.16的权重。
Okay. I basically get a floing 0.16 weights.
我将使用FP16的权重来进行前向计算。
I'm going to use fpin 16 weights to do forward competion.
这很好，因为如果你还记得在浮点运算中的ODS产品说明书，
This is pretty good because if you still remember the ODS product sheet in flopping,
呃，我认为16位的浮点运算能力比32位高得多。
uh, I think 16 bit is much more higher flops than 32 bits.
你可以使用16位张量进行计算。
You can use 16 bit tensor word competion.
并且因为你使用的权重和激活都是浮点0.16的权重，
And because you use weight and activation is both in flowing 0.16 weights,
你也会得到浮点0.16权重的激活值。
you are going to also produce flowing 0.16 weight activations.
好的。同样地，我将用这16位的权重和激活来做反向传播，好吗？
Okay. And similarly, I'm going to use this 16 bits of weights and activation to do backward, okay?
这样我就会得到，基本上会产生浮点0.16的梯度，对吧？
That will give me, that will basically produce um gradients, right, that is in flowing 0.16. Okay.
那么问题基本上就停留在这里。
Then the problem basically last here.
所以当我们尝试将这些梯度应用到我们的参数二时。
So when we try to apply these gradients into our priamter two.
好的，我们要做的基本上是，我们会拿这些梯度，然后应用
Okay. What we do is basically, we will take this gradings, and we are going to apply
这个浮点0.16到这个主权重上，用来更新这个主权重到下一个版本。
this floating 0.16 into this master weight to upload to update this master weight
我们应用的方式基本上是，我们会把它提升精度。
into version next version.
我们会把它从16位提升到32位。
And the way we apply it basically, we are going to upcast it.
好吗？我们基本上只会在
We are going to upcast from 16 bits into 32 bits.
更高的精度下进行这种权重更新，
Okay? We are going to basically only do this kind of weight update at
以确保我们保持精度，并且能够对动态范围具有鲁棒性。
higher precision to make sure we preserve precision and we can basically be robust to dynamic range.
好的，这就是核心思想。
Okay. This is a halo idea.
但是当我们把这个应用到Adam上的时候，麻烦的地方就来了。
But the dirty part happens when we apply this to Adam.
明白吗？因为记住，在Adam中，呃，
Okay? Because remember in Adam, uh,
Adam是我们用来优化神经网络的默认优化器。
Adam is the default optimism we use for optimize neural networks.
当我们应用这个方法时，我觉得这样就可以了，
And when we apply this I think for this, we are good, right,
因为这基本上是针对反向传播的。
because it's basically for the backward.
这和Adam没有关系。
It's not relevant with atom.
但当我们把这个应用到Adam时，会发生什么呢？如果你还记得Adam的话，
But when we apply this into Adam, what happens is, if you still remember in Adam,
嗯，我们有两个矩，没错吧。
um, we have two moments, right.
我们需要计算一阶和二阶矩，然后用这些矩来归一化
We need to calculate the first and second moments, and we use those moments to basically normalize
我们的梯度，然后再把它应用到原始的w上。
our gradient libit and then apply it into the original version of the w. Okay.
现在让我们看看如何在Adam中应用这个方法。好的。
And now let's see how we apply this in Adam. Okay.
我还是会用这个作为例子。
So I will still use this as an example.
所以训练GBD三，因为这是最好的例子，
So training GBD three, because this is the best example
能帮助你理解发生了什么。
that will help you understand what's going on.
好的，我们关心的是当我们使用这种混合精度训练
Okay, um, and what we care about is when we use this mixed precision training,
框架时，实际上会用多少内存？
um, framework, uh, how many memory will actually use?
我们能节省多少内存，对吧？
How many memory we can save, right?
因为我们的最终目标是通过合并来节省内存，好吗？
Because our eventual goal is, um, we want to save memory through conation, okay?
简单回顾一下，对吧？
So just a little bit recap, right?
针对最大的模型，
For the largest model,
175B，我们需要用16位来存储权重，对吗？
175 B, we need to store the weights in 16 bits, right?
那就是350G的激活值，你在MCQ里做过这个，对吧？
So which is 350 giga activations, you did this in MCQ, right?
所以我们在边界处做检查点保存。
So we checkpoint at the boundary.
我们得到了这么多激活值，对吧？
We get this many of activations, okay?
问题在于最优权重。
The problem is optimal weights.
所以我不确定你还记不记得之前内存那节课，我们讲过多少内存
So I'm not sure if you still remember in previous lecture in the memory lecture how many memory
我们需要用于最优状态。
we need for optimal states.
我们有梯度，对吧？我们有一阶矩和二阶矩，对吧？
We have grading, right? We have first moment and second moment, right?
好的，所以基本上，就是三份数值，每个数值都会以目标精度保存。
Okay. So basically, uh, uh, three copies of values and each value will be sip in a target precision.
好吗？现在我们试着把这个应用到混合精度训练框架中。
Okay? Now, let's try to apply this in our mixed precision training framework.
好吗？所以当我们应用混合精度训练时，情况就发生了变化。
Okay? So when we apply mixed precision training, the story changes here.
我们不能用FP16来表示权重，对吧，因为我们要保证精度。
We cannot see weight in FP 16, right, because we want to preserve accuracy.
所以我们必须保留一份主权重的副本，对吧，就像这个图里显示的那样。
Okay? So we have to maintain a copy of master weight, right, in this figure.
这份副本基本上是四，四位，对吧，32位，四位乘以175。
Okay? So this copy is basically four, four bits, right, 32 bits, four bits times 175.
这是700G，好吗？
This is 700 giga, okay?
所以这里我们有一个四倍的因子，因为我们用LP16内核进行计算。
So here we have a factor of four Um, because we perform competition using our LP 16 inter core.
所以我们都会针对参数生成一份梯度的副本，
So we all produce a copy of gradients against the perimeter,
而这份梯度的副本就是用P16保存的，就在这里。
and this copy of gradients is saved in P 16, right here.
所以这里我们有一个二倍的因子，就是我们用16位生成的原始梯度副本。
Okay? So we have a factor two here, which is the original copy of gradients we produce at 16 bit.
好的，我们还需要有一个持续更新的副本，也就是说我们需要以某种方式持续运行。
Okay. And we also need to have a running copy that is we need to somehow run
复制这个，然后把这个复制应用到我们的权重上。
this copy and apply this copy to our wt.
明白了吗？所以又是一个因子2。
Okay? So another factor two.
这里的秘诀其实就是，当你在Adam中应用混合精度时，你还必须存储
And the secret here is basically when you apply this mixed precision in atom, you have to also store
第一和第二矩以更高的精度。
the first and second moments in higher precision.
因为记住，归一化最终你是想用
Because remember, malization eventually you want to use
这个第一和第二矩来做归一化。
this first and second moment to normalization.
基本上就是对梯度进行归一化，好吗？
Basically lomize gradients, okay?
而归一化对精度和动态范围都非常敏感。
And the lomization is very sensitive to precision and also to, uh, dmic range.
所以我们也必须用高精度来存储这个第一和第二矩。
So we have to also store this first and second moment in high precision.
所以在这里我们又得到了一个4乘2的因子，好吗？
So here we get another factor of four times two, okay?
然后我们又得到了一个八倍的因子。
And we get another factor eight.
好吗？这就是我们的做法。
Okay? This is what we do.
当我们应用这些开放状态时，我们需要保存什么。
What do we need to save when we apply this open states.
在这里，我要给你们讲这节课中最重要的信息之一。
So here, I'm giving you one of the most important message in this lecture.
好的，你需要记住这一点。
Okay, you need to remember this.
所以当我们训练语言模型时，呃，我们所需的内存下限就是这个。
So when we train language models, um, the memory we need is lower bounded by this one.
好的，这基本上就是第一个四倍因子，第二个因子是梯度，
Okay? And this is basically the first factor of four second factor gradients,
运行副本、第一阶矩、第二阶矩。
running copy, first moment, second moment.
好的，这才是真正训练语言模型时的内存使用情况。
Okay. This is the real real memory usage for train language models.
是的，因为在我之前的讲座中，
Yeah, because in my previous lecture,
我从未提到过混合前置训练，但现在我基本上是在告诉你，
I never mentioned the mixed preceding training, but now I'm basically tell you,
我们实际上正在使用混合前置训练。
we're actually using mixed preceding training.
这意味着，你最终得到了16倍的因子。
So which means that, uh, you ended up with a factor of 16
N。这里的N是你的amber参数，也就是一份amber参数的拷贝。
N. We N is your amber parameters, one copy of amber parameters.
为什么这个公式如此重要？
Why is this equation so important?
因为下次当别人问你，我能用H100训练一个模型吗？
Because next time when people ask you, can I train a model using H 100?
我能在H100上训练Lama 7B吗？
Can I train Lama seven B on H 100?
在单个H100上，你立刻就明白了，
On single H 100, you immediately know,
比如你有一个7B的Lama模型，你用7乘以16，
I use this, say, you have a seven B model Lama, and you use seven times 16
这样你就知道了你所需的最低内存是多少。
and you know the lower bound memory that you need.
显然，这个数字大于80GB，这意味着你无法
Which is apparently this number is greater than 80 gigat that means you are not able to
在单个H100上训练Lama 7B。
train Lama seven B on single H 100.
好的，这样说有道理吗？
Okay. Does it. Does it make sense?
好的，所以一定要记住这一点，好吗？
Okay. So make sure you remember this, okay?
这是训练语言模型的下限，好吗？
This is the lower bound for training language models, okay?
任何框架都一样。它适用于Petro，也适用于TensorFlow、JAX，任何框架。
Any framework, yeah. It apples to Petro, you apply to tender flow jacks, any framework.
为什么要复制梯度？
Why you copy gradients?
因为一方面，你需要用权重梯度来推导激活梯度。
Because, on one hand, you need to derive the activation gradients using weed gradits.
你必须保存它。另一方面，当你把梯度应用到主网络时，
You have to save that. On the other hand, when you apply that gradient to the primary,
为了进行类型提升，你需要复制以进行类型提升。对，对吧？
how to upcast it, you need to copy to upcast. Yeah. Yeah. Okay?
好的，16。这还没有考虑激活值。
Okay, 16. And this is not considering activations.
明白吗？所以如果你也想考虑激活值，你需要回到这张幻灯片，然后尝试
Okay? So if you want to also consider activations, you need to go back to this slide and try
多研究一下这个内容。
to study this a little bit.
好吗？我们如何保存激活值。
Okay? So how we save activations.
很好。记住这个。
Cool. Okay, memorize this.
我认为这非常重要。
I think this is extremely important. Okay.
好的，这基本上就是我关于量化，或者更广泛地说，精简机器学习的讲座总结。
Yeah, that basically wrap up my lecture on quantuon or more broadly, skinning down machine learning.
我想花几分钟来谈谈这个领域。
I want to spend a few minutes to talk about this area.
基本上，精简机器学习和深度学习
So basically skinning down machine learning and deep learning is
是机器学习和系统领域非常活跃的研究方向。
a very active area of research in machearing and systems.
很多教授、学生都在做这件事，对吧？
A lot of people a lot of professors, students are doing this, okay?
因为在边缘设备上运行机器学习一直有很强的需求，对吧？
So because running machine learning on edge devices is always strongly demanded, right?
我觉得每个人都想这么做。
I think everyone wants to do that.
这就是为什么在这个规模上有很高的需求，对吧？
That's why there's a high demand on this scale, okay?
但我想指出的一点是，嗯，这个缩小规模的市场，
But one thing that I want to point out is, um, uh, this market of scaling down
它有一个非常关键的特性。
merginary it has a very key characteristics.
好吧？这是一个非常分散的市场。
Okay? It's a very fragmented market.
那么我说的分散市场是什么意思呢？
So what do I mean by fragmented market?
我是在和云市场做对比，云市场是我们边际扩展的地方。
So I'm comparing this to cloud market where we scale up marginally.
好的，所以如果你想想云市场，它一点也不分散，对吧？
Okay. So why is if you think about cloud market, it's not fragmented at all, right?
基本上，AWS 占有 70% 的市场份额，对吧？
Basically, AWS has 70%, uh, market share, right?
然后是 GCP 和微软。
And then GCP and Microsoft.
好的，三大巨头，明白了。
Okay, three, big three, okay.
但是如果你说要精简硬件的话，其实没有真正的赢家，对吧？
But if you talk about skinning down marchiney there's no, like, a winner, okay?
所以每家公司都在做自己的事情。为什么呢？
So everyone is doing their own thing. Why?
因为在云端，我们只有通用芯片。
Because in Cloud, we only have media chips.
明白吗？我们大致上都是部署通用芯片。
Okay? We roughly deploy everything, media chips.
而在云端，AWS 是唯一的赢家。
And in Cloud, AWS is the only winner.
你可能也知道，是的。
You probably know, yeah.
但是当你谈到精简硬件时，芯片的种类就非常多样了。
But when you talk about screen down, there are so many diverse chips.
我想在上一节课，我们的气体讲座变更等等，呃，呃，
I think in the previous lecture, our gas lecture change et cetera, uh, uh,
当我们进行合并编译时，主要的问题是有太多不同的芯片
when we do merginy compilation, the main problem is there are so many different chips
你必须对比到不同的，比如内核库或者其他东西，对吧？
that you have to compare down to different, like, kernel libraries or whatever, right?
所以这是一个非常分散的市场，这意味着如果你选择在这个领域做研究，
So it's a very frag market market, which means that if you choose to do research in this area,
发表论文很容易，因为总是有问题存在。
it's very easy to publish because there's always a problem.
对，针对目标硬件。
Right, for target hardware.
是的，因为从业人员不够多。
Yeah, because there are not enough people.
如果你选择在这个领域做生意，
And if you choose to do a business in this area,
我会说这是个不错的生意，特别是对于初创公司来说，
I would say it's a good business, right, because especially for startups,
因为你总是可以选择一个尚未被充分关注的目标领域，
right, because you can always choose a target domain which is under addressed,
然后你试图帮他们解决问题。
and you try to address the problem for them.
的确，这是一个非常不错的领域，你可以在这里创业并被收购。
Indeed, this is a pretty good, um, uh, area that you can build a startup and get
我可以给你举个例子。
acquired. I can give you an example.
Ten chi，对吧，他的公司AutoML，在英特尔芯片上表现得相当不错。
Ten chi right, his company AutoML, they do pretty well on Intel chips.
我觉得在某个时候，他们收到了英特尔一个很不错的收购报价。
And I think at some point, they got a pretty good offer from Intel, to acquire them.
但他们拒绝了，因为他们想做得更大。
But they declined, because they want to do bigger.
他们想要更大的发展，对吧？最终市场会发生变化。
They want, right? Eventually market changes.
好的，另一个例子是，一位做定量的教授，就是我提到的Songha的公司，
Okay. Another example is, um, a mating professor, the quantititi guy, I mentioned Songhas company,
他在条件方面做了很多工作，对吧？
and he's doing condition a lot, right?
他基本上就是条件领域的引路人。
He's a guide of condition, basically.
他为Avidia和高通做了很多冷凝工作，对吧？
And he does a lot of condensation work for Avidia and for Qualcomm, okay?
他基本上是针对
He basically optimize against
英伟达芯片和高通芯片进行优化。
Nvidia chips and Qualcomm chips.
结果证明他非常成功。
And it turns out that he was very successful.
我记得在2022年，他的公司被英伟达收购了，对吧？
I think in 2022, his company was acquired by Nvidia, okay?
我听说他同时收到了高通和英伟达的两个报价。
I heard that he got two offers from both, like, Quadcom and Nvidia.
好的，他选择在2022年去Avidia，对吧？
Okay, he chose to go A Midia in 2022, okay?
这笔交易相当不错，对吧？
That's a pretty good deal, good deal, right?
因为在2022年，WIDA芯片，
Because in 2022, WIDA Chip,
Amdatock还在，对吧？嗯，好的？
Amdatock is still here, right? Yeah, okay?
我也有一些朋友在做这种生意，他们基本上会选择，
And I also have a few friends which do this kind of business, and they basically choose,
硬件厂商，因为你知道，现在的硬件厂商非常有钱，对吧？
hardware winder because, you know, hardware winder lot is very rich today, right?
他们有很多资金，想要收购各种小公司。
And they have a lot of money. They want to acquire every small companies.
他们的目标基本上就是那些速度快的硬件。
And they basically target that speed hardware.
他们会为这些硬件做非常深入的定制或实现，
They try to do very deep, like don or implementation for them hardware,
然后希望被收购。他们一直都是这样。
and they hope to be acquired. And they always.
好吧？但坏消息是，如果你真的想做一家非常大的公司，
Okay? But the bad news is, um, if you really want to build a really big business,
比如像谷歌、亚马逊那么大，我觉得这不是
for example, as large as Google, as a Amazon, I don't think this is
一个适合做大事业的领域，因为就像我说的，这很容易
a good area for doing that because like I said, it's very easy to it's very
很难把所有芯片统一起来，对吧？
difficult to unify every chips, right?
你必须为一种类型的压缩设计
You have to design one type of condensation
一套算法和一个针对某种硬件的内核库。
and algorithm and a kernel library for one typo hardware.
这个领域非常非常碎片化，所以每个人都在做自己的事情。
It's very very fragmented, so everybody is doing their own.
明白吗？嗯，就研究方向而言，
Okay? Um, and in terms of research direction,
我认为这个领域还有很多事情在发生，因为每次有新模型出现，
I think there are still a lot of going on because every time there's a new model,
每当有新硬件，或者有新类型的内核算子出现，
when there's a new hardware, when there's a new kind of kernel operator,
量化领域的人基本上都会去尝试这些东西。
quanta people is going to basically tact them.
是的，他们可能会为此做好准备。
Yeah, they are going to probably feel prepared for that.
明白吗？而且大家在这个领域做了很多工作，比如量化和剪枝，
Okay? And people are doing a lot in this area, for example, quantadon pruning,
因为你最终是想把你的模型部署到边缘设备上，对吧？
because you eventually want to deploy your ID devices, right,
你开始关注能量，好吧，能量效率。
you start care about energy, okay, energy efficiency.
你还会做联邦加工，
And you also do federation machining,
好的，这在本次讲座中没有涉及。
Okay, which was not covered in this lecture.
但很遗憾，我们聘请了一位新教师。
But unfortunately, we hired a faculty.
他将在今年秋天加入我们。
He's going to join this fall.
是的，他是做量子编辑的，好吗？
Yeah, he's a quant editing guy, okay?
如果你感兴趣，可以去听听他的课，好吗？
And if you're interested, you can try to listen to his classes, okay?
很好。这就是我关于量子编辑的全部内容。
Cool. That's all from me on quant edition.
好的，那我们继续，好吗？
Okay. Then let's move on, okay?
整体情况。所以我们完成了
Big picture. So we finish
DataFgraph 右侧是 AutoDvGraph Oenation。
DataFgraph right AutoDvGraph Oenation.
我们还会更深入地探讨算子 Oenation。
We also dive deeper into operator Oenation.
嗯，我们还会开始讨论运行时，如何进行调度，如何管理内存，如何做量化。
Uh, we also start talking about run time, how to schedule, how to do memory, how to do quantition.
好吗？现在，我觉得我们要进入最后一个大型讲座部分 Paradition，对吧？
Okay? Now, I think we are going to enter our last big lecture Paradition, right?
好的。受到启发，我想要涵盖这么多内容，可以吗？
Okay. Inspired I want to cover this many content, okay?
我会解释为什么我们需要开始学习 paraldition。
I'm going to justify why we need to start why we need to study paraldition.
然后我会讲讲机器学习中的并行性，以及
Then I'm going to talk about machine learning parallelism and
如何讨论连接通信，因为这是机器学习并行性的基石。
how to talk about connective communication because it's a cornerstone for machine learning paralism.
好吗？然后我们开始讨论并学习所有这些数据模型，
Okay? And then we start talking about and study all this data model
操作符间中断并行性，我们就此总结。
interoperator interrupted palism we wrap up,
嗯，通过回顾一些关于自动并行的最新研究。
uh, by reviewing some latest work on automatic parallon.
好的，酷。那么我们为什么需要活塞呢？
Okay. Cool. So why we need piston?
我觉得我们基本上需要回到我们的主线故事。
I think we basically need to come back to our mainstream story.
慢一点。所以，我认为我们应该在开始讨论的时候做这件事
More slow. So, I think we should do this when we start talking about when
当我们开始论证加速器的必要性时。
we start justify accelerators.
好的。所以二十年前，是的，我们还有摩尔定律，但现在已经停止了，对吧？
Okay. So 20 years ago, yes, we are still having the more slow, but now it stopped, right?
同时在机械行业，发生了什么呢，好吧。
Okay. Meanwhile in machinery industry, what happened is, Okay.
模型的规模基本上每18个月增长十倍，太疯狂了。
The model size, they are basically ten times every 18 months. It's crazy.
而且这条曲线还在继续。
And this curve is still going on.
最新的TipSIg模型有6000亿个参数，好吧。
The latest TipSIg model is 600 biniar perimeters, okay.
基本上，佣兵模型的规模正在疯狂增长，为什么人们开始开发这些大型模型？
So basically the size of mercenary model is growing crazily, why people start developing
有两个原因。
all these large models? Two reasons why.
一个原因是，通过简单地增加模型的规模，
One is because, um, by simply skiing the size of the models,
你会得到更好的性能表现。
you are going to have a way better performance.
这里，横轴表示模型的参数数量。
So here, the excess is the number of parameters of the model.
纵轴表示在20个自然语言基准测试中的平均表现，
The Y excess is the average performance of 20 benchmarks in literal language,
呃，呃，自然语言处理。
uh, uh, literal language processing.
所以你不用在意具体的基准测试是什么。
So you don't care about what the benchmark.
基本上，我们把它标准化到0%到100%之间。
Basically, we normalize that into from 0% to 100%.
好的，100%就是完美表现。
Okay. 100% is perfect performance.
零基本上就是零表现。
Zero is basically the zero performance.
一旦我们进行了归一化，你会发现当我们调整模型规模时，好吗？
And once we normalize it you observe that when we skill the model size, okay?
当我们尝试在这20个基准测试上测量平均表现时，你会看到基本上
And we try to measure the average performance on all these 20 benchmarks, you will see basically
性能会持续提升。
the performance will just keep increasing.
好的。好的，这让人有希望，对吧，因为如果你能达到100%，你基本上就实现了AI。
Okay. Okay, this gives hope, right, because if you can achieve 100%, you are basically achieving AI.
真正的通用人工智能。好的，这就是第一个原因。
True AGI. Okay. That's the first reason.
好的，增加模型规模可以带来很大的性能提升。很简单。
Okay, Skinny model size can give you a lot of performance improvement. That's simple.
第二点是人们开始观察到大型模型具有一些涌现能力，
The second is people start observing that big models have some emergent capability,
我真的很喜欢谷歌制作的这个动图，好吗？
and I really like this Jif produced, um, by Google, okay?
这个动图想要说明的其实是，当你不断扩大模型规模时，
So what is this Jif try to illustrate is basically, when you continue to skill the model sizes,
能够完成一些非常复杂的任务。
Be able to do some very complicated tasks.
好的，所以这有点像是一次飞跃。
Okay. So this is kind of like a leap pas leap forward.
就像一个婴儿，每隔几个月就会发展出一项新技能。
It's like a baby that every few months, it's going to develop a new skill.
突然之间，是的。好的。人们确实观察到了这一点。
Suddenly, yeah. Okay. And people indeed observe this.
如今，我认为人们已经在讨论一些非常高级的技能，比如推理，
Today, I think people are already talking about some very advanced skills, reasoning,
当你以某种方式扩展你的模型，并且你的模型开始推理时，
When you skill your model in some way and your model start to reason,
开始解决这种数学问题，对吧？
start to solve this kind of mathematical questions, okay?
不，我要做的基本上是对齐我应该对齐的两条曲线。
No. I try to do is basically I'm going to align the two curves I should.
一条是模型的规模。
One is the model sizes.
另一条是芯片的能力。
The other is chips capability.
这是模型的规模，每18个月增长十倍。
This is the model sizes, ten X every 18 months.
这是摩尔定律，你可以看到差距正在扩大，扩大了很多，
This is the Morse law, you can see the gap is widening, a lot of widening,
这意味着摩尔定律将不再适用，
Which means that Morse law is not going to work,
摩尔定律基本上是描述CPU发展的，好吗。
Morse law is basically characterized in the development of CPU, okay.
好的。我希望你还记得我的这张幻灯片，对吧？所以我们有两个选择。
Okay. I hope you still remember my slide this slide, right? So we have two options.
一个是加速器，另一个是量子计算，而且量子计算正在进行中，
One is accelerator. The other is quantum computing, and quantum computing is going on,
我们基本上可以把我们的加速器故事映射到那条曲线上，好吗。
and we can basically project our accelerator story into that curve. Okay.
如果我们预测加速器能力的增长，
And if we project the growth of the capability of accelerators,
结果基本上还是差距很大，对吧？
what happens is basically still wide gap, right?
它基本上处于我们所需和当前CPU实际提供之间的中间位置。
It's basically in the middle of what we need and what we actually what CPU current currently offer.
好吗？所以VD GPU的增长，计算能力还是
Okay? So the growth of the VD GPU, the compute flops is still
赶不上需求，对吧？这是个问题。
not catching up, okay? That's a problem.
而TPU的增长曲线，比GPU稍微好一些。
And the TPU curve green curves a little bit better than GPU.
明白吗？嗯，很好。而且这个差距每18个月会扩大256倍。
Okay? Yeah. Cool. And this gap is increasing, uh, 256 times every 18 months.
是的。所以基本上，如果你只用一个加速器，
Yeah. So basically, all the accelerators, if you use a single accelerator,
你是追不上我们需要开发的模型规模的。
you're not going to catch up with the model sizes we need to develop.
明白吗？这是从计算的角度来看。
Okay? And this is from the compute perspective.
你也可以从内存的角度画出类似的曲线。
And you can also draw this kind of curve on from a memory perspective.
实际上发生的情况是，内存的增长更加疯狂，对吧？
What happens is basically, um, the memory increase even crazier, okay?
所以我们需要的内存，用来存储和训练模型，基本上……
So the memory that we need to store the model to train the model basically,
嗯，它每两年增长35倍。
uh, it increase 35 times every two years.
但是GPU内存的增长要平缓得多，对吧？
But the GPU memory girls is much flatter, okay?
所以基本上，你根本无法赶上这个速度，对吧。
So basically, there's no way that you can catch up. Okay.
而且能在单个GB上运行的最大模型，基本上我们停在了BRT。
And the largest model fit on single GB basically we stop at BRT.
好的，BRT基本上就是我们能在单个GI上存储的模型，对吧？
Okay. BRT is basically the model that we can store on single GI, okay?
然后在某个时刻，我们基本上会遇到变化。
And at some point, we basically face the change.
那就是我们仅仅存储参数就需要超过100个
That is we need more than 100
GPU，还不包括那些优化器状态和激活值，对吧？
GPOs to just store the parameters, not mentioning those openmeter states and activations, okay?
是的，我希望这个图，这是真实的数据，对吧？
Yeah, I hope this figure this is real data, okay?
这是真实的数据，不是说
This real data, it's not like
我编造了这个，好吧，是真实数据。
I made up this, okay, real data.
我希望这基本上能证明没有其他出路，对吧？
And I hope it's basically justify that there's no way out, right?
我们唯一能做的就是进行部分相加。
The only way that we do is basically we do part addition.
这就是为什么我们需要学习并行化，好吗？
That's why we need to study paraliztion, okay?
很好，那我们来谈谈部分相加。
Cool. Then let's talk about part addition.
好的，我想你们很多人可能已经在做这部分了，对吧？
Okay. So I think many of you probably already worked on this part, right?
就像，如果你用Petro，或者你今天做其他类似的事情，
Like, if you do Petro you do whatever kind of thing today,
你们可能已经开始使用
you probably have already started working with like
Petroc分布式或者Tinder flow分布式这类库了，对吧。
Petroc distributed or Tinder flow distributed kind of library, right.
而且，我觉得你们大多数人在做这个的时候
And, um, and I think most of you when you work on this,
基本上你会接触到两个概念。
you are basically educated with two concepts.
一个叫做数据并行。
One is called data parism.
另一个叫做任务并行。
The other is called the Mtopism.
那么什么是数据并行和任务并行呢？明白了吗？
So what is data palism and topolism? Okay?
我认为数据并行很容易理解，我们一直在讨论这个，
I think the dataparism is very easy to understand we have been talking about that at
在加速层面上，基本上就是SIMD。
the accelerated levels basically SIMD.
比如GPU里有很多很多核心，你把每一部分数据分配给不同的核心。
Uh I GPU you hold many many cores you give each part of data.
这基本上就是数据并行。
That is basically data parism.
在本节课的这个部分，数据并行的意思是你有很多很多不同的GPU，
And in this part of the lecture, uh, data paralisis means that you have many many different GPUs,
你把每一部分数据分配给每一个GPU。其实是一样的。
you give each GPU a part of data. It's the same.
所以在数据并行中，我们有很多很多的GPU。
So in data parism we have many many GPUs.
每个GPU可能都安装在某些节点上，对吧？
Each GPU is probably installed on some notes, right?
我们有一个巨大的数据集。
And we have a huge dataset.
基本上我们把数据集拆分，然后给每个GPU分配一个部分数据集，
And we basically split the data set and we give each GPU a paro dataset,
让它们一起处理，好吗，同时并行处理。好。
and we let them proceed together, okay, in parallel. Okay.
所以这里，数据并行实际上有一个核心假设，就是整个模型需要
So here, Datapism actually has a core assumption that is, uh, the entire model needs to
能够放在一台机器或一块GPU上。
fit on a single machine or GPU.
好的。那么如果模型无法放在一台机器上会发生什么呢？
Okay. So what happens, if the model does not fit on a single machine?
那基本上就需要多机并行了。
That basically give us multipis
我们需要对模型进行分区。
We need to party in the model.
好吗？所以，这意味着我们需要对模型本身进行并行化。那么，什么是模型呢？
Okay? So, meaning that we need to paralyze the model itself. So what is the model?
因为在这节课中，我认为我们已经知道这个模型是什么了。
Because in this lecture, I think we know what this model.
它基本上是一个计算图，我们定义了那个通信图，
It's basically computer graph, we define that comminute graph,
我们稍后会再回到这个问题。
and we are going to come back to that later.
但是，假设这是一个未标记的模型。
But however, say, this is a unla model.
它基本上包含了很多数学模型，许多许多非线性函数，
It's basically a lot of mat model, many many non linear functions,
嗯，就像组成了完整的计算图一样。
uh, like composing complete computer graph.
好的。那么当我们谈论如何对这些模型进行划分时，
Okay. So when we talk about, uh, how we basically partition these models,
我们其实是在讨论如何划分这些张量操作，对吧？
we are talking about how we partitioning this kind of tensor operators, right?
直观上来说，有几种方式可以实现。
So intuitively, there are a few ways, okay?
一种方法是我们可以从中间切开，对吧？
One is like we can cut in the middle, right?
比如说这个模型有四层，我们基本上从中间切开。
So say this general has four layers, we basically cut in the middle.
我们把前两层分给第一个GPU，后两层分给另一个GPU，对吧？
We give the first GPU two layers, the other GPU another two layers, right?
这就是第一种模型类型。
This is a model type number one.
好的。另一种方式是，我们甚至可以进行流水线执行，
Okay. Another way is, um, we can even pipeline execution
这样会更复杂但更高效，不过我们可以之后再讨论这个，好吗？
to make it even more complicated but more efficient, but we can talk about this layer, okay?
嗯，好。那么做模型分区的第二种方式是什么？
Um, Okay. And what's the second way of doing mod party?
所以这是一种垂直切分，对吧？
So this is vertical cut right.
我也可以做水平切分。
I can do horizontal cut.
好的，是的，这其实很直观。
Okay? Yeah, so it's very intuitive.
我也可以进行横向切分。
I can also horizontal cut.
所以对于每一层，我会把那一层切成不同的部分，然后把每个部分分配给每个GPU。
So for each layer, I'm going to cut that layer into different parts and I give each GB a part.
明白吗？这其实是另一种类型的模型并行方式，好吗？
Okay? This is another part of another type of mod partism, okay?
你可以看到，这会变得相当复杂，因为每一层可能有
And you can see this can become rather complicated because each layer probably has
不同类型的算子，而且每个神经网络可能有不同类型的层，对吧？
different kind of operators and each neural network probably have different kind of layers, right?
我们还有不同类型的集群。
And we also have a different type of cluster.
我们可以有一个节点上安装了八个GPU的集群。
We could have a cluster with eight GPUs installed in one node.
我们也可以有一个非常大的集群，里面有成千上万个GPU，
We can also have a pretty big cluster where we have tens of thousands of GPUs,
并且它们以不同的方式分布。
and they are distributed in different ways.
这样一来，问题就会变得非常复杂。
Okay? And that will basically make the problem very complicated.
这就是我们接下来要深入探讨的内容。
And that's what we are going to dive deeper.
好的。但直观上，我觉得就像我说的，你有一个经典的机器学习划分视角。
Okay. But intuitively, I think, like I said, uh, you have a classic view of machine learning partism
你把划分分为数据划分、多重划分。
where you classify pism into data parts, Multi partism.
我觉得接下来我要做的，就是把这种
And I think next, what I'm going to do is I'm going to map this kind of like
对划分的直观解释映射到我们对模型、数据和计算的定义上，对吧？
intuitive explanation of pism into our definition of models and data on compute, right?
因为我们希望从纯计算和系统的角度来研究这个划分问题。
Because we want to approach this pism from sure computation and system perspective.
这样我们就知道在系统层面该怎么处理了。
So we know what to do what to deal with on system side.
好的，还是回顾一下，对吧？
Okay. Still recap, right?
这是我第二节课用到的图，我们有神经网络，
This is the figure we use in my second lecture, where we have neural networks and
这个神经网络可以用这个主方程来表示，对吧？
this neural network can be represented using this master equation, right?
还记得每个符号的定义吗？
Still remember the definition of each symbol.
记得。
Okay.
那么从计算的角度来看，partsm是什么？
So from a computational perspective, what is partsm?
好吗？我觉得从计算的角度来看，我们关心两件事，对吧？
Okay? I think from a computation perspective, we care about two things, right?
一是如何计算。
One is how to compute.
如何计算计算图。第二是内存。
How to compute the computer graph. Second is memory.
我希望我们花这么多时间在内存上，主要是为了确保
I hope we spend so many time on memory, how to basically make sure
计算能够受限于峰值内存。
the computation will subject to the peak memory.
好吗？所以对于计算机来说，如果你看这个方程，呃，哪些元素需要计算？
Okay? So for computer, if you look at this equation, uh, what are the elements that require compute?
第一个元素是这个函数，它执行前向和反向计算。
The first element is this function, which perform forward and backward.
好吗？当我们谈论并行化时，基本上需要在这个计算函数中分成两部分，
Okay? And when we talk about parism, we basically need to parts in this compute function across
跨越不同数量的设备。明白吗？
different number of dips. Okay?
第二部分是F操作很重要，对吧？我们在这里对参数应用梯度。
A second part is the F op matters, right, where we apply gradients, uh, two parameters.
我们需要应用这个函数
And we need to apply this function
F。我们需要在不同的设备上执行这个函数F。
F. We need to perform this function F across different dipts.
好吗？这就是这个方程的主要计算部分。
Okay? And this is the main compute from this equation.
好，我们将学习如何进行并行化。
Okay, we are going to study how to parallelism.
在内存部分，我们有两个主要的消耗来源，一个是D，
On the memory part, we have two main sources of consumption is D,
D是数据，批次数量。
D is data, number batches.
如果你对D进行分区，它就变成了数据并行，很清楚。
And if you partition D, it becomes data pismV clear.
好吗？Theta，Theta 基本上就是参数。
Okay? And Theta, Theta is basically the uh parameters.
好吗？我们需要对参数进行分区，因为我们无法将整个模型放在一个 GPU 上。
Okay? We need to partition parameters because we cannot put the model into one GPU.
内存不够用。
The memory is not sufficient.
好的。我们真正需要研究和关注的一个部分是通信。
Okay. And one part that we really need to study and take care of is, um, communication.
为什么通信很重要？因为在单个设备上，你确实有通信，但是
Why communication is important because on a single device, you do have communication, but
通信基本上发生在内存层级之间。
communication basically happens between memory hierarchy.
你在不同的内存之间进行通信，比如，
You communicate between, uh,
从 CPU 内存到 HBM、SRAM，再到缓存、再到寄存器。
CPU memory to HPM SRM to catch it to register.
这完全是本地的。
Okay. And that is pure local.
所以你的设备，比如你的 GPU 库像 Coda，会为你提供所有这些内存拷贝的功能。
So your device, uh your GPU library like Coda, they provide all this kind of memory copy for you.
实现起来非常容易。
It's very easy to implement.
但是当你分布式处理时，情况就不一样了，你必须在
But when you go distributed this different story, you have to communicate these things across
不同的GPU之间进行通信，以及不同的节点是如何连接的。
different GPUs and how different dips get connected.
设备之间有一些互连，这种互连可能是，
There is some interconnect between devices, and this interconnect could be,
如果你把GPU放在一个机箱里，就是Medius Vlink。
medius Vlink if you put GPUs in one box.
或者如果你想继续扩展规模，就必须通过网络。
Or if you want to continue to scale up, you have to go through the network.
网络的话，有不同类型的网络。
Network, you have different kind of networks.
你有亚马逊的，比如弹性结构这样的网络技术。
You have Amazons, like elastic fabric, this kind of network technology.
你也有Infinivn。
You also have infinivn.
如果你学过网络，你会知道还有TCP/IP这种，基本上有很多层。
You have TCP IP kind of basically many layers if you have studied networking.
那么该如何处理通信呢。
Then how to handle communication.
这也是分布式系统中主要的复杂性来源。
And that is the main source of complexity in poison.
所以我们要非常小心地处理通信，因为我们知道通信比本地操作要慢得多，
So how to carefully handle communication because we know communication is much slower than locality,
因为本地操作只是内存层级之间的移动。
because locality, you just moves between memory hierarchy.
但一旦开始通信，延迟就会很高。
But once you start doing communication, you have a high latency.
明白吗？我们必须处理这个问题。
Okay? We have to handle that.
还有如何处理通信参数，以及，呃，
And how to handle communication parameters and also, uh,
通信激活，这取决于
the communication activations, and that depends on
我们如何划分神经网络，也就是计算图。
how we partition the new network, the computation graph.
明白吗？这些内容会在内部讲到，我们现在先了解一下高层次上我们要做什么。
Okay? So that'll be inside, um, we know what do we do at a high level.
那么我们基本上可以尝试从这个角度来理解数据和多路并行，
Then we can basically try to understand data and multipaism from this perspective,
从计算机的角度来看。
from this computer perspective.
对于数据并行，我们要做的基本上就是对数据进行分区。
So for data parism, what we do is basically we are going to partition the data.
我们会把数据分成不同的部分，然后分配给每个GPU。
We are going to piton the data and we give each GPU
每个GPU拿到不同的数据，然后各自进行计算，对吧？
different data and they compute on their own, right?
但问题是，每个GPU虽然各自计算，
But the problem is, um, each GPU is going to compute on their own,
但在某个时刻，它们需要进行同步。
but at some point, they need to synchronize.
否则，每个GPU基本上都是按照自己的节奏在计算，
Because otherwise, GPU is basically computer on their own pace and they are
并没有真正为同一个任务做出贡献。
not basically contributing to the same job.
你通过分区其实并没有取得进展。
You are not making progress through partition.
所以我在数据分配时，需要沟通哪些内容。
So I datapati what kind of thing will need to communicate.
我们很快就会弄清楚。基本上我们需要搞清楚的部分，
We are going to soon figure out. So basically the part that we need to figure out
是如何传递参数和输入数据，对吧？
is how to communicate the parameters and ingredients, okay?
还有整个算法，所以基本上，我们把数据分成不同部分，对吧？
And the entire algorithm, um, so basically, we part in the data, okay?
我们给每个GPU分配不同的数据，同时也复制参数。
We give HGPU a different data where we also replicate the parameters.
所以我们给每个GPU一份参数的副本。
So we give each GPU a copy of the parameters.
明白了吗？然后GPU会拿到参数的副本，
Okay? And then GPU is going to take the copy the parameters,
当然还有模型代码的副本。
and also a copy of the model code, of course, okay.
然后它会在指定的数据批次上执行计算。
And it's going to apply this computation on that specific designated batch of data.
完成这些后，我们会得到什么结果？
And once we do this, what we'll produce?
我们会生成一份梯度的副本，对吧？
We will produce a copy of gradients, right?
记住，在这个优化过程中，我们需要做的是把
And remember in this optimization, what we do is we need to apply
梯度应用到参数上，对吧？
the gradients into primeters, right?
所以HTPU可以独立地把梯度应用到参数上。
So HTPU could apply the gradients independently to the parameters.
但这样做没有意义，因为否则，
But it does not make sense, because otherwise,
EHPU做的，嗯，换句话说，GPU基本上是在各自为政。
EHPU is doing, um, in other way, GPU is basically doing their own communion.
没有任何通信。所以我们在daal纯粹主义中要做的是，
There's no communication. So what do we do is basically in daal purism,
我们要同步梯度。
we are going to synchronize the gradients.
好吗？我们会有一个通信机制，在这个机制下我们会连接
Okay? We are going to have a communication mechanism where we are going to connect gradients
所有GPU的梯度。
from all the GPUs.
我们先累积它们，然后再应用到参数上。
We accumulate them, and then we apply to the parameters.
好的。当我们应用到参数上后，我们会得到一份新的参数副本。
Okay. And once we apply to the parameters, we are going to get a new copy of the parameters
然后我们基本上会把这份参数副本分发给DPS，然后开始下一次迭代。
and we basically redistribute that copy of parameters to DPS, and we start next iteration.
明白了吗？这就是数据并行。
Okay? This is data partarism.
而在模型并行的情况下，事情会变得更复杂，对吧？
And I Mdparism things becomes more complicated, okay?
所以，我们不再对数据进行分区了。
So, we don't partition data anymore.
明白了吗？我们要对模型进行分区。
Okay? We are going to partition the model.
嗯，对模型进行分区其实是非常薄弱的，对吧？
Uh Partitioning model is very, very weak, right?
那么我说的模型并行是什么意思呢？
So what do I mean by parison model?
其实有很多很多种可能性。
There are many many possibilities.
一个是我要对模型参数进行分区，也就是Theta。
One is I'm going to partition the model parameters, which is the Theta.
另一个是我要对竞争进行分区，也就是那个函数。
The other one is I'm going to petition the competition, which is that function.
好的，Lambda L，明白吗？
Okay. Lambda L, okay?
这里的问题是我们如何处理数据？
The problem here is how do we deal with data?
对吧？因为在多分区的情况下，
Right? Because in multiparism,
我不知道该如何处理数据。
I don't know how to deal with data.
我可以分区，也可以不分区。
I could parts or not partition.
好的，我们会想办法解决的。
Okay. We are going to figure it out.
当然，我们还需要对优化器状态进行分区，因为我们已经对模型的一部分进行了分区，
And, of course, we need to partition optiber states because we already part in part of
并且我们必须将部分梯度应用到部分参数上。
the model and we have to apply the partial gradients into the part of parameters.
好的，我们进行分区。好的。
Okay, we partition. Okay.
嗯，这样你就能看到全局了，对吧？其实很复杂。
Uh, that'll give you a big picture, right? It's very complicated.
好的。你有很多分区的选择，同时还要受网络延迟的影响。
Okay. You have so many choices to petition, and you also subject to networking latency.
你还受内存限制的影响，还受其他各种因素的影响，
You subject to memory constraints, you subject to whatever,
比如说，呃，这些都会让你的任务变慢，明白吗？
like, uh, well, make your job slow, okay?
你必须确保以聪明的方式进行分区，这样你的任务才不会变慢。
You have to make sure, uh, you petition in a smart way that your job is not slow.
明白吗？这就是问题的一部分。
Okay? This is part of the issue.
好的，现在我基本上要开始讲一下我们如何
Okay, now, I'm going to basically start talking about how we
让整个流程变得更加清晰。
make this entire picture much more clear.
好的。所以我希望你还记得这个图，对吧？
Okay. So I hope you still remember this figure, right?
所以我们可以用计算图来表示我们的模型，这个计算图基本上是
So we can represent our model using a computer graph, and this computer graph basically is
由三部分组成：前向、反向和更新。
composed of three parts forward, backward and with update.
好的，最终我们会得到这个图。
Okay. And eventually we'll end up with this graph.
好的，那什么是paradisi？
Okay. So what is paradisi?
所以如果你只是在模型层面上思考paradisi，
So if you only talk about if you think that paradiing at the model level,
你是无法弄明白的。
you're not going to figure it out.
因为这太复杂了，有太多不同类型的模型。
Okay, it's too complicated because there are so many different kind of models.
所以现在，让我们换一种思维方式。
So now, let's basically change your mindset.
我们先不考虑模型本身。
We forget about the model.
好吗？所有的模型基本上都是计算图。
Okay? All the model are basically computer graph.
好的。我会给你一张计算机图，你只需要仿照它。这就是仿照。
Okay. I'm going to give you a computer graph, you just paradi it. That's paradion.
好吗？所以在这节课里，我要讲的内容是，
Okay? So in this lecture, what I'm going to the way I taught I taught is,
我要教你如何仿照，基本上我会给你这张计算机图。
I'm going to teach parodies basically I'm going to give you this computer graph.
我还会给你一个像这样的设备集群。
I'm also going to give you a device cluster like this.
我觉得集群很容易理解，特别是给你这个集群。
I think cluster is very easy to read, especially given to this cluster.
比如说，这是Medius DGX盒子，这是V100，
For example, this is the medius DGX box, and this is V 100,
但基本上E100和H100是一样的。
but basically E 100 and H 100 is the same.
它们的连接方式让你可以看到这个GPU。
They are connected in a way where you can see this GPU.
好的。而HGPU基本上有多路连接，这种连接带宽非常高。
Okay. And HGPU basically has a multi way link, this Mink is very high bandwidth.
也就是说，当HGPU和这个盒子里的其他GPU通信时，
Meaning that HGPU when they talk to another GPU inside of this box is
非常高带宽的通信，非常非常快。
very high bandwidth communication. Very very fast.
这几乎就像是一个内存层次结构，只是稍微慢一点。
It's almost like a memory hierarchy, but just a little bit slower.
好的，但如果你在这里再画一个框，如果这个GPU想和另一个GPU通信，
Okay. But if you draw another box here and if this GPU wants to communicate with another GPU here,
问题就出现了，他们必须通过这个互联网。
the problem exists, they have to go through this Internet.
他们必须把数据从GPU内存转移到CPU内存，然后
They have to move things from GPU memory to CP memory and let
让CPU通过这个互联网发送这些内容。
the CPU to send those contents through this Internet.
你可以看到通信带宽的规模。
And you can see the scale of the communication bandwidth.
互联网几乎比链路慢十到一百倍。
Internet is almost like ten to 100 times slower than link.
好的，也许我可以把这个再抽象一点，就是我们有这样一个集群。
Okay. And maybe I can make this a little bit more abstract, that is, we have this kind of cluster.
这里我有四个节点，可以吗？
Here I have four nodes, okay?
一、二、三、四，对吧？
One, two, three, four, right?
基本上每个节点有几个GPU，这里我写了四个，但现在通常是八个，好吧。
And basically each node has a few GPUs here I give four, but typically today is eight, okay.
这些GPU之间有高速连接，我这里用绿色线表示。
These GPUs are basically have a fast connection, which I use green green line here.
如果你想让不同机箱里的GPU之间通信，
And if you want to communicate between any GPU that is from different boxes,
你就必须通过慢速连接。
you have to subject to the slow connection.
好的。通过这样重复的设备集群，
Okay. And with this repenton of this device cluster, um,
那么我们的问题就变得稍微
then our problem is become a little bit more,
我觉得，比之前的版本更好了。
I would say, nicer than previous version.
就是说，呃，好吧。
That is, uh Okay.
所以这部分基本上等同于在设备集群上划分计算图。
So part of this basically equals to partitioning computational graph on device Claster.
好吗？在左边，我们有一个计算机图。
Okay? On the left hand side, we are given committer graph.
好吗？在右边，我们有另一个图，但这个图不是计算机图。
Okay? On the right hand side, we are given another graph, but this graph is not a computer graph.
它基本上是设备的图。好的。
It's basically graph of devices. Okay.
在这里，我没有用图这个词，但你可以这样理解，好吗？
And here, I don't use graph, but you can understand it that way, okay?
这个图有一个非常独特且确定的特征，就是在一个盒子内部，
And this graph has a very unique and very determined characteristics that is inside of one box,
是快速连接，而盒子之间是慢速连接。
it's fast connection and between boxes store connection.
我们的问题基本上是如何在设备集群上划分计算机图。
And our problem is basically how to partition commuter graph on the device clasor.
好的，问题定义完毕。
Okay? Problem defined.
好，有什么问题吗？
Okay. Any question?
当然，你还需要满足内存限制，对吧？
Of course, you need to subject to memory constraints, right?
你需要服从，比如说，通信带宽。而你希望你的作业能够完成。
You need to subject to, for example, communicating bandwis. And you want your job.
一旦你在这个设备集群上对图进行了划分，你希望你的作业能够
Once you partition this graph on this device cluster, you want your job to run as
尽可能快地运行，并且没有自动内存管理。
fast as possible without auto memory.
明白了吗？很好。在明确了这个问题后，我们开始聊一聊如何划分这个问题。
Okay? Cool. With this defined problem, let's start talking about a little bit on how to partin this.
好的，这里我将开始讲解如何划分图。
Okay, here, I'm going to start talking about how to paten graphs.
为了简化一点，
To simpfy a little bit,
我会给你一个非常简单的图，好吗？
I'm going to give you a very simple graph, okay?
在这个图里，你有，嗯，这就是我们在
So here in this graph, you have, um, this is the one we used in
上一节课中用到的，基本上是一个单层的MLP。
the previous lecture it basically single layer MLP.
好的，呃，有两个中间节点m1u和一个MSC，两个权重是W1、W2，还有一个输入X。
Okay? Uh, two met m1u and one MSC, two is W one, W two, and one input X.
但和我之前的讲座相比，这里我要引入更多的旋转。
But compared to my previous lecture, here, I'm going to introduce a little bit more rotation.
我要给每个节点分配一个颜色。
I'm going to give each node a color.
这里我有一个由两个节点组成的集群，
So here I have a cluster of two nodes,
设备一和设备二，蓝色代表第一个设备，粉色代表第二个设备，
Device one and device two, and blue is the first device and pink is the second device,
如果一个节点是某种颜色，说明这个节点、这个操作、这个计算发生在那个设备上。
if a node is one color, that means that node that operator, that computation happens on that device.
明白了吗？这样说清楚吗？很好。那么用这种表示法，我们可以开始对这个图进行分区，
Okay? Does that make sense? Cool. Then this notation, we can start partitioning this graph,
我们还可以用符号表示，分区线上我们做了什么？
and we can use notation to notate, what do we do on the partitioning bar?
好，这是我们的第一个策略。
Okay. This is our first strategy.
如果你还记得前面几页幻灯片，我是在中间切开的。
If you still remember a few slides before, I cut in the middle.
我是在不同层之间切开的，
I cut in between different layers,
我把前两层分配给一个设备，另外两层分配给第二个设备。
I give the first two layers to one device and another two layers in the second device.
所以在这里，如果我在策略中反映这一部分，基本上就是这样。我在中间切开。
So here, if I reflect that part in strategy is basically this one. I cut in the middle.
我把第一个元件分配给蓝色设备，基本上把第二个和第二个记忆分配
I give the first met to the blue device, and I give basically the due and second memo
给第二个设备。我在中间切开。
to the second device. I cut it in the middle.
我用不同的颜色。策略一，好的。
I use different color. Strategy one, okay.
我其实可以做一些不同的，比如我可以做一个水平切割。
And I can basically do slightly different, for example, I can do a horizontal cut.
我把权重W1，
I put the weight W one,
W2放在第一个设备上，其余的放在第二个设备上。
W two on first device, and I put the rest on on second device.
所以记住，当我们在中间切开时，当那两个节点正好在一半的位置，
So remember, when we cut in the middle when those two nodes where the halfway at,
如果它们在不同的设备上，会发生什么？
if they are on different devices, what would happen?
他们需要沟通，对吧？
They need to communicate, right?
他们需要沟通。我们接下来还会再讲这一部分，但是
They need to communicate. And we're going to, with this part again, but
我们先假设我们已经知道如何沟通了。
let's assume that we know how to communicate.
好的。所以我会说这两种策略是一样的，因为
Okay. So I would say the two strategy is the same because
我实际上就是把那些笔记分开了，
I actually basically cut those notes,
我把不同的笔记放在不同的设备上。
I put different notes on different devices.
那你能给我一个不同的策略吗？
So could you give me a different strategy?
如果你还记得我之前幻灯片里的直观幻灯片，
So if you remember in my previous slides in intuitive slide,
我也可以切割水平卡片，把一层切成一半或者一半的网络。
I also can cut horital card I cut a layer into half or one half network.
那对于那张卡片，它对应的是这两种中的哪一种？
So for that card, does that card correspond to one of these two?
一个，你觉得是一个吗？
One, you think is one?
不，这不是一个，因为在其他切分中，
No, it's not one, because in other cut,
我基本上把备忘录分成了两部分。
I basically cut the metmo I cut the memo into two parts.
而在这两个图中，我实际上根本没有切分备忘录。
And in these two figures, I actually don't cut memo at all.
备忘录总是在一个设备上整体执行。
The metamo is always perform as a whole on one device.
这意味着如果我尝试切分算子，
Which means that if I try to cut operators,
我实际上会采用不同的策略，比如这样。
I actually have a different strategy like this.
所以这里我用这种符号表示得更直观一些，也就是说我要切分
So here I use this notation a little bit more intuitively, that is I'm going to cut
算子，我会把算子分成两半，用不同的颜色表示，一半在
operator I'm going to give the operator half and half different colors, and one half is performed on
一个设备上执行，另一半则在不同的设备上执行。
one device and then the other half is performing different devices.
所以你要弄清楚怎么解析这一部分。
So you figure out how to parse that one.
呃，如果你看这部分，它的意思是对于这个met more，好吗？
Uh, if you look at this part, it means that for this met more, okay?
我打算从中间切开。
I'm going to cut in the middle.
我把met more的前半部分放在一个设备上，后半部分放在另一个设备上。
I put the first half of the met more on one device, the second half on second devices.
因为我切开了metam，输入和输出也需要切开，对吧？
Be I cut metam the input and output also need to be cut, right?
所以因为我想执行metam的前半部分，也就是mat，
So because I want to perform the first half of the metam which is mat,
我想在第一个设备上执行mat。
I want to perform mat on the first device.
所以我也得把输入切成两半，对吧？
So I have to also cut the input into two half, right?
这部分将会执行Mt。
And this part is going to perform Mt.
好的，然后第二个设备将会执行more，明白吗？
Okay. And the second device is going to perform more. Okay.
所以我也需要剪掉这个输出。
So I also need to cut this output.
抱歉，是另一部分输入，对吗？
Sorry, another part of input, right?
然后你要操作粉色条。
And you're going to perform the pink bar.
好的。这样说得通吧？
Okay. Makes sense, right?
酷。还有别的方法吗？
Cool. Is there a different way?
当然，我可以在操作层面做一个横向切割。
Of course, I can do a horizontal cart at operating level.
抱歉，这个颜色有点儿，看不太清，但你明白我的意思。
So sorry this color is a little bit, uh, not working, but you get it.
我基本上可以这样切，对吧？
I can basically cut in this way, right?
对，所以对于
Yeah. And so for
Metamor，我可以基本上按照不同的轴来切割，a，这样会导致
Metamor I can cut basically following different axes, a, it will result into
不同类型的分割策略。
different kind of parting strategies.
好的，这一页有问题吗？
Okay. Any question on this slide?
很好。那么这里，我将介绍两种略有不同的策略。
Cool. So here, I'm going to introduce two slightly different strategy.
明白吗？在第一行，
Okay? So in the first row,
我基本上采用了一种不切割操作符的策略。
I'm basically applying a strategy where I don't cut operators.
我只切割图结构，明白吗？
I only cut the graph. Okay?
我把这种策略称为操作符间分割。
And I call this strategy interoperatd pism.
呃，你应该能推断出这个名字的含义，对吧？
Uh, you can infer the meaning of this lame, right?
操作符间分割基本上意味着
Interoperator parism basically means that
我从不切割操作符。
I never cut an operator.
我基本上只是切割了图。
I basically only cut the graph.
我把图的不同节点分配到不同的设备上。
I assign different nodes of the graph to different devices.
在第二行，我调用了跨操作的棱镜。
And in the second row, I called the interoperative pism.
也就是说，我要接触这个算子。
That is, I'm going to touch the operator.
我要在两个不同的设备上执行同一个算子，然后我会
I'm going to perform one operator on two different devices and I figure
想办法之后聚合结果。
out how to aggregate results later.
好的，你可以看到跨操作棱镜的定义，
Okay. Um, you can see the definition of interoperative prism and
跨操作棱镜我觉得比数据和多操作棱镜
inter operative parism is much I would say much more or
要模糊得多。
less uh ambiguous compared to data and motpoism.
为什么？当我谈论多操作棱镜时，你们不知道我指的是什么。
Why? I motoparism when I talk about Mtoparism, don't know what I mean.
你可能不知道，因为“我”可以有很多很多种意思。
You probably don't know, because I can mean many many things.
但当我谈到 inter 和 intra 时，这是非常精确的。
But when I talk about inter and interoperats, it's very precise.
Inter 基本上意味着我不会切操作符，但 intra 意味着我会这么做。
Interbasically means, I'm not going to cut operator, but intra means I'm going to do that.
好的，那我问你一个问题。
Okay. Then let me ask you a question.
那么 datapism 是 inter 还是 intraoperative parism？
So is datapism inter or intraoperative parism?
请问，Intra 是 Inter 吗？
Please. Is Intra Inter?
Intra？是的，Datab 是 intra，为什么？
Intra? Yes, Datab intra Why?
因为你切了 X，而 X 是你的节点，你确实切了 X，X 是你的输入。
Because you cut X and X is your node, and you indeed cut X X is your input.
你切的是批次，所以是 intra。
You cut batches, so it's intra.
好的，我们会一遍又一遍地回到这个问题上。
Okay. We're going to come back to this again again.
好吗？我们将要探索所有不同的Inter和Intra策略。
Okay? We are going to explore all different strategies of Inter intra.
我们将要推理它们的权衡，比如通信量有多少。
We are going to reason it trade off, how much it communicate.
需要多少内存，明白吗？
How many memory it needs, okay?
好的。基于这些定义，让我稍微展开一下intra和intraparism。
Okay. And given these definitions, uh, let me expand intra and intraparism a little bit.
对于矩阵，我们实际上可以对其进行划分，比如我们可以做行划分，好吗？
So for matrix, we can actually partition it along, um, we can do row parison, okay?
我们也可以做列划分。
We can also do column pion.
抱歉，这个颜色不一样，显示不出来。我来修一下。
Sorry, this color is different, it's not working. I'm going to fix it.
我的意思是，你可以这样切，也可以那样切。
But what I mean, basically, you can cut it in this way or you can cut it in this way.
这个我称为行划分，
Okay. I call this row partition,
这个我称为列划分，明白吗？
I call this column partition. Okay.
所以我将引入第三个定义和第三种颜色，这代表我可以复制它。
So I'm going to introduce a third definition and a third color, which I could replicate it.
这意味着我并没有切分它。
Which means that I'm not cutting.
好的，我基本上是在复制这个张量。
Okay. I'm basically replicating this tenser.
如果这个颜色是绿色，表示我正在把这个节点复制到两个设备上。
Okay. If this color is green, it means that I'm replicating this note on both devices.
所以每个设备都会有它的一个副本。
So each device will have a copy of it.
好的，按照这个位置，我们可以可视化更多的并行策略。
Okay. So following this location, we can visualize more parlement strategies. Okay.
接下来，我将可视化一些著名的并行策略。
And next, I'm going to basically visualize a few notable parliament strategies.
基本上，接下来我要展示的每种策略都是非常著名的论文提出的，
And basically each strategy I'm going to visualize next is very famous paper,
超过一千个站点，好吗？
more than 1,000 stations, okay?
并且它们已经被应用在训练中了。
And they are being adopted in training.
我这样做的原因是因为我想向你们展示，我们可以用这个图形来说明很多很多不同的概念，明白吗？
The reason I do this is because I want to show you that we can use
这个图形基本上可以用来说明许多不同的概念，好吗？
this repenton to basically illustrate many, many different concepts, okay?
那么第一个。嗯，请你们看它10秒钟，
So the first one. Um, plea you look at it for 10 seconds,
然后我会问你们这是什么。
and I'm going to ask you what what this is.
有人想回答吗？
Anyone want to answer?
其实我刚刚已经讲过这个了。
I actually talked about this right now.
这是什么？对，数据对比。
What is this? Yeah, data parison.
好的，你答对了。为什么是数据对比？
Okay. You got it. Why is data parison?
因为我有两个设备，对吧？
Because I have two devices, right?
我复制了宽度，对吗？
I replicate the width, right?
这意味着每个设备都有一份width的副本。
Which means that each device has a copy of width.
我在输入中进行了分区。
And I part in the input.
因为我在输入中分区，所以这个metamo也会被分区，对吧？
Because I part in the input, so this metamo is going to be partin as well, right?
这种分区会一直在神经网络中传播下去。
All the way like propagated through this neural network.
所以每个设备都会计算不同的损失。
So each device is going to calculate different loss.
我跳过了绿色更新部分，但我们稍后会回到这一点。
And I skip the update green update part, but we'll come back to that later.
明白了吗？这就是数据并行，好吗。
Okay? This is data parison, okay.
我希望你们在听完我的讲解后，回去尝试
I hope you basically after my lecture, you go back and try to
理解这种重复，因为它非常重要。
internalize this repetition because it's very important.
我们将把这个过程变得任意复杂。
We are going to make this arbitrarily complicated.
好吗？那这个怎么样？
Okay? How about this one?
有人做过M吗？不，是这个。
Anyone work on M No, this one.
抱歉，这是某种modoparism类型。
Sorry. Is is one type of modoparism.
那是什么类型？好的？这是我在阅读megaton时给你的那个。
What is that type? Okay? This is the one I give it to you in reading megaton.
好的。通常，人们把这种modopoism叫做张量并行。
Okay. And typically, people call this kind of modopoism tensor partism.
好的？它叫做张量并行，是当今语言模型训练中常用的一种并行方式。
Okay? It's called tensor partism it is a typical pism used in today's language model training.
你会注意到，这里我们不是复制权重，
And one thing you'll notice that is here instead of replicating
而是复制输入。
weights we are replicating the input.
基本上，每个设备都会得到一份输入的副本，
And basically, each device is going to get a copy of the input,
然后我们会分开处理权重。好吗？
and we are going to patina weight. Okay?
另外因为我们给权重做了氧化处理，所以我们也会参与到元数据中，好吗？
And also because we patina weight, we are also going to part in the meto, okay?
然后我们还会把所有分区一直传播到下一个元数据模块。
And then we also propagate all the partitions all the way to next met moo.
但对于下一个元数据模块，我们会复制备忘录。
But for the next Mtmo we are going to replicate the memo.
好的。嗯。好的。我想让你把这个和我给你的阅读材料结合起来理解，
Okay. Yeah. Okay. I want you to cross boons this into the reading I give it to you,
必读材料，就是那篇microtome的论文。
the required reading, which is microtome paper.
那这个呢？好，这个稍微抽象一点，但我可以告诉你。
How about this one? Okay. This is a little bit more abstract, but I can tell you.
这个本质上是流水线并行，你在这里注意到的主要是，
This one is essentially pipeline parism the thing that you notice here is basically,
我没有做内部并行，
I don't do intraperparism,
我从不做分区操作。
I never parting operator.
但我做的基本上是，嗯，
But what I do is basically, um,
我在这里把 M 分成了两部分，我在中间切开了。
I part in this met M. I cut in the middle.
我给每个设备分配了不同的 metmo。
I give each device a different metmo.
与此同时，我用很长的时间来流水线执行 metam。
Meanwhile, I pipeline execution of metam using a long time.
每次我都会给一个批次，这个批次首先进入第一个设备。
Each time I'm going to give a batch and this batch first comes into the first device.
然后当第一个设备的 metm 完成后，它会把计算结果
And then once the first device metm finished, it will forward the computation
或者激活传递到第二个设备。
or the activation to the second device.
同时，在下一个时间步，这个设备会去获取
Meanwhile, in the next time step, this device is going to fetch
另一个批次来进行并行计算。
another batch to the parallel competion.
这基本上就是流水线并行。明白了吗？
This is basically pipeline parism. Okay.
那这个呢？这个就更疯狂了，对吧？
How about this one? This is even crazier, right?
不，我有四个设备。
No, I have four devices.
好的。设备三和设备四，它们使用了不同的颜色。
Okay. And device three and device four, they are using different colors.
好的。这个我不太会称它为三G对比，但它非常复杂。
Okay. This one is called I wouldn't call it three G parison, but it's very complicated.
的确，这是我们现在用于语言模型训练和GBD训练的方法。
Indeed, this is something that we use today for language model training for GBD training.
你会注意到的事情是
The thing you'll notice that is
我手里有四个设备，对吧？
I hold four devices, right?
我的做法是我先把我的设备分成两组。
What I do is I first cut my devices group into two groups.
第一组是这组，蓝色和红色。
The first group is this group, blue and red.
第二组是绿色和黄色。
Second is green and yellow.
我的做法是，如果你把这两组看作一个超级设备或者设备组，
And what I do is if you think of these two as one mega device or device group,
我首先做的是进入互操作分区，我会从中间切开。
what I do is I first to enter of inter operative partism, I cut in the middle.
我把这部分Nork分给第一组，把这部分N分给第二组。
I give this part of Nork to the first group and I give this part of N to the second group.
好的。如果你把这两个设备看作一个元设备，这就是纯粹的互操作分区。
Okay. And if you think this two device are one meta device, this is pure interpartim.
但我没有用这个设备组，而是继续做内部操作分区。
But instead of this device group, what I do is I continue to do intraop partism.
好的？我基本上在第一组内做列分区，把第一组的两个设备分开，
Okay? I basically cut in column parison, for the first group, the two device in the first group,
然后我在第二组再做一次列分区，明白吗？
and I do another column party in the second group. Okay?
这比较复杂，因为它本质上结合了互操作和内部操作分区，涉及更多设备。
This is rather complicated because it essentially combines inter and intra op pismoO more devices.
现在，人们把这种方式称为分区，好吗？
And today, people give the name that is parism, okay?
如果你想训练非常大的模型，
And um if you want to train really large model,
比如说用超过1000块GPU，这就是你的首选方法。
for example, on more than 1,000 GPUs, this is your to go.
接下来我会进行解释。
I'm going to explain next.
好的。那么我还有最后一页幻灯片要讲，来解释为什么我花了这么多时间给你做这个入职培训。
Okay. Then I have one last slide to explain why I spent
为什么我们如此关注intra和intra。
so much time to onboard you on this orientation.
但在那之前，我想先做个小结，好吗？
Why we care about intra and intra.
对于中断式划分，我们基本上是把不同的算子分配到不同的设备上。
But before that, I want to summarie a little bit okay.
对于中断式划分，我们是把单个算子的不同区域分配到不同的设备上。
For interrupted partism we basically assign different operators to different devices.
这个很容易理解。
For interrupted partism we assign different regions of a single operator to different devices.
好的，现在让我们看看，如果我们把这两种划分方式应用到一个小的计算图上，计算模式到底是什么样的。
And that's easy to understand.
现在我们来尝试看看，如果我们把这两种划分方式应用到一个小的计算图上，计算模式到底是什么样的。
Okay. Now, let's try to see what the computational pattern really looks like if we apply
these two types of partism to a small graph.
好的，我们现在要更深入地探讨这个划分。
Okay, we are going to dive deeper into this partition and
我们基本上是在思考GPU上会发生什么。
we basically thinking in a way that what happens on GPU.
好吗？这是最重要的幻灯片之一。
Okay? And this is one of the most important slides.
所以一定要确保你理解了它。
So make sure you understand it.
如果你不明白，来问我，我会尽量解释清楚。
And if you don't understand, come to ask me, I try to explain this.
好的，来看这个有五个节点的图。
Okay. Consider this graph with five notes.
这个图是我通过跳过al和MSE得到的。
Okay. I got this graph by basically skipping the al and the MSE.
我让它变得更简单了。
I make it even simpler.
好的，嗯，
Okay. Um,
实际上，这个图本质上是在做两个矩阵变换，就像这个方程所示。
So in fact, this graph is essentially doing two matrix modifications as this equation shows.
好的，我希望你基本上能够内化这张图上的这个方程，对吧？
Okay, I want you to basically internalize this equation on this graph, right?
所以在这里，我基本上把W分成了两个设备的两部分，对吧？
So here, I basically partition the W into two devices into two parts, right?
然后我复制了X。
And I replicate X.
我喜欢每一份
And I like each copy of
X列分区的W，这基本上也会给我，我还会分区另一个呃W和W二，
X column partition the W which will basically give me, also I do partition another uh W and W two,
然后我把它们绑定在不同的设备上。
and I tie them together on different devices.
我让每一部分都来自不同的设备。
I make each part from different devices.
明白了吗？明白，这个方程，对吧？
Okay? Okay, with this equation, right?
很好。好的。
Cool. Okay.
我们来看看设备上发生了什么。
Let's see what's happening on device.
好的。我们从第一份备忘录开始。
Okay. Let's start from the first memo.
那我们就从这个开始。那么在这里
So let's start with this one. So here
我知道X是被复制的，对吧？
I know X is replicated, right?
这意味着设备一和设备二都会有X的副本。
So which means both device one and two will have copy x.
好的？那么W1的方式是列分区的，对吧？
Okay? So the way W one, it is column partition, right?
这意味着设备一拥有W1的左半部分，对吧？
So which means that device one has the left part of W one, right?
设备二拥有W1的右半部分。
And Device two has the right part of W one.
好的？所以X是被复制的，对吧？
Okay? So X is replicated, right?
所以每个设备都有X和W的左/右部分。
So each device has X Left par W par, W. Okay?
我们要进行矩阵乘法。那么我们会得到什么？
We are going to perform at the mall. So what do we get?
我们把它们绑在一起，对吧？
We tie them together, right?
对于第一个设备，我会得到Mdmal结果的前半部分，
For the first device, I'm going to get the first half of the Mdmal result,
也就是met，对于第二个设备，
which is met, for the second device,
我会得到Mdm M的后半部分，这就是为什么在这个表示法中，
I'm going to get the second half of Mdm M, that's why basically in this notation,
我得到了这个met和M。这就是我们的结果。
I get this met and M. It's our result.
我们基本上可以在这里检查这个分区的结果。
And we can basically check the result here the partition here.
我们发现这个met基本上对应这个met，而这个mo对应small，
We find that basically this met corresponds to this met and this mo correspond with small,
没有问题，它们是对齐的。我们没问题。
there's no problem it aligns. We're good.
我们将继续进行下一个meth mod。
We are going to proceed to the next meth mod.
好的。好的。在下一个met模式中，我们从这个开始。
Okay. Okay. In the next met mode, we start with this.
好吗？不，我们直接进入这里吧。
Okay? No, let's move right into here.
好的，看看这个。
Okay. Look at this one.
好的，在这个图中，我们说对于第一个设备，
Okay. So in this figure, we said that we are going to for the first device,
我们将使用met，对于第二个设备，我们将使用mod，同时，
we are going to have met for the second device, we are going to have mod, meanwhile, uh,
对于这个W2，对吧，我们基本上做一个低分割，好吗？
for this W two, right, we basically do a low parting, okay?
这意味着对于第一个设备，我们有W2的上半部分，对吧？
Which means that for the first device, we have the upper part of W two, right?
对于第二个设备，我们有W2的下半部分，好吗？
For the second device, we have the lower part of W two, okay?
那我们要做什么？我们要做乘法器运算。
And what do we do we are going to do the multiplier.
好的，如果我们这样做会发生什么？
Okay? So what are happen if we do this?
那我们都会得到一个矩阵met M，它的完整形状和原始metamo是一样的。
So we all get a matrix met M, which is the full shape of the same shape of the original metamo.
但是它们的数值是不同的。
But their values are different.
因为如果你还记得我们的Mdm交叉，这个叫做部分和，对吧？
Because if you still remember our Mdm cross, this is called partial sum, right?
所以invintu金属值应该是我们要把这两个加起来
So the invintu metal value should be we should add these two
一起加起来，就是invent memo，对吧？
together together the invent memo, right?
好的。然后我们要做的是，我们再次检查这个。
Okay. Then what we do is, again, we're going to check this.
这是我们执行后得到的结果，对吧？
This is what we get if we execute it right.
这是我们在图上预期的结果，对吧？
And this is what we expect on graph, right?
好吗？我们要在这个上面检查一下。
Okay? We are going to check this on this.
那我们来检查一下，好吗？
So let's check it, okay?
所以在这个里面，每个设备基本上得到一个部分和。
So on this one, each device basically get a partial sum.
但在这个图中，我们希望每个设备都获得元数据的副本。
But on this graph, we want each device to get a replica of the met.
那么我们如何从这里过渡到这里，如何满足对每个手机的约束？
So how we can transition from here to here, how we can satisfy the constraint on life handset.
我们要把它们加在一起，对吧？那要怎么加在一起呢？
We add them together, right? So how to add them together?
所以为了把它们加在一起，
So in order to add them together,
我需要第一个设备把这个纯和发送给第二个设备，对吧？
I need the first device to send this pure sum to the second device, right?
同时，我需要第二个设备把这个和发送给第一个设备。
And meanwhile, I need to second device to send this pum to the first device.
也就是说，我需要这种操作。
That is, I need this kind of operation.
也就是对我来说有用，对我来说有用。
That is using to me and using to me.
然后我自己做求和，可以吗？
And then I do the summation myself, okay?
对吧？这就是我最小化通信的方法。
Right? That's the way that I minimize communication.
好吗？基本上是什么操作来执行这个操作？
Okay? What operation basically perform this operation?
什么样的通信操作能满足这个约束？这叫做归约（reduce）。
What kind of communication operation will satisfy this constraint? It's called reduce.
好吗？你们知道归约吧？
Okay? You guys know reduce, right?
好的。如果你不知道也没关系。
Okay. If you don't know, it's fine.
我会在下个学期教你们。好的。
I'm going to teach you next quarter. Okay.
但不是下个学期，是下节课。
But not next quarter, next class.
好的。但本质上，在这里，你可以看到。
Okay. But essentially, here, you can see.
当我进行这种分区时，
When I do this kind of partition,
我推导出什么样的执行，
I derive what execution,
我会尝试看看如何满足这种分区方式。
I try to see how I can satisfy this kind of partitioning.
我最终发现我其实需要用reduce，这个reduce基本上就是
And I eventually found that I actually need reduce, this reduce is basically how
pardon处理这种分区的方式。
pardon handles this kind of partitioning.
好的。我们来看第二个例子。
Yeah. Okay? Let's look at second example.
好的，请说。策略。
Yeah, please. Strategy.
抱歉，是这个策略。
Sorry. This strategy.
这是一个好策略吗？
Is this a good strategy.
这是一个好策略。这就是Mctron。
This is a good strategy. This is the Mctron.
是的，是的。它确实很慢，因为你需要用reduce，而reduce是一个非常耗费资源的操作，
Yeah. Yeah. It's pretty slow, because you need to reduce and reduce is a very expensive operation,
但没有更便宜的方法了。
but there's no cheaper way.
因为最终，我要把这个转化成最优问题。
Because eventually, I'm going to convert this into optimal problem.
我将证明这是最优的方法。
I will prove this is the optimal way.
你做不到更好。明白吗？没有道理。
You cannot do better. Okay? Doesn't make sense.
好的，我们假设这就是我们想要的。
Yeah, let's assume that this is what we want.
但我想解释为什么我们需要这样做，因为为了进行下一个操作，
But I want to explain why we need this because in order to perform the next palm,
如何让这个要求在这个副本之后得到满足。
how to have this met following this replica.
好的。那么我将用最后一个例子来结束我的讲解
Yeah. Okay. Then I'm going to finish my lecture using one final example
下一个例子会更简单。
and the next example is going to be easier.
这是历史上的另一部分，我称之为“并行化”。其实很简单。
This is another part of history, which I call inter paralization. It's pretty simple.
在第一个设备上发生的事情基本上是，对于后续的学者，我知道
What happens on first device is basically uh, for following scholar, I know
这个备忘录将在第一个设备上执行。
this memo is going to perform on the first device.
它基本上有这两个输入，X在W上，一个是本地的。
And it basically has these two input X on W one local.
那么在第一个设备上发生的事情是X，输入1，我在第一个设备上得到了备忘录的结果。
So what happens on the first device is X, types one, I get the memo results on the first device.
然后我开始把我的I移到第二个备忘录里。
And then I start moving my I into the second memo.
在这里，我希望我的第二个备忘录发生在第二个设备上，也就是红色的设备上。
Here I want my second memo to happen on the second device, the red device.
所以，在第二个设备上，
So here, in the second device,
我有这个W2，这也是本地的，对吧？
I have this W two, which is also local, right?
而且我希望我的结果被写入第二个设备。
And I want my results to be written in the second device.
但我发现我缺少了我的输入，对吧？
But I find that I'm missing my input, right?
这个输入在哪里呢？就在第一个设备上，对吧？
And this input where it is, is on the first device here, right?
那么为了满足这种计算需求，我该怎么办？
So in order to satisfy this kind of competion, what I do?
我还通过这里的通信模式变化来进行交流。
I also communicate by the communicating pattern changes here.
我做的是让第一个设备直接把更多的结果发送给第二个设备。
What I do is I ask the first device to send the more results directly to the second device.
明白了吗？这就是我做的，对吧？
Okay? That's what I did, right?
这被称为点对点通信。
This is called P to P communication.
这是一种与前面那种稍有不同的通信模式。
This is a slightly different communicating pattern from this one.
在前面那种模式中，我需要每个设备都与其他设备通信。
In this one, I need every device to communicate with the other device.
但在这种模式下，我只需要一个设备与另一个设备通信。
But in this one, I only need one device to communicate to the other.
一个是发送方，另一个是接收方。
One is sender, the other is receiver.
我想你现在已经发现它们的区别了。
I think now you already spot the difference.
我现在要给你一个陈述。
I'm going to give you a statement.
对于手术中的分区操作，只要你进行这种操作员分区，
So for intraoperative partism, as long as you do this kind of operator partitioning,
你就会引入一些连接通信。
you are going to deduce some connective communication.
但对于这种互操作性，如果你不在操作员中分区，而是在图中分区，
But for this interoperatism, if you don't party in operator, you always part in a graph,
你只需要点对点通信。
you only need PTP communication.
这基本上给你带来了一个关键的区别，因为不同的通信方式成本差异很大。
That basically give you a key difference because different communication have very different cost.
降维操作比点对点通信要昂贵得多，这需要映射到
A reduce is much, much more expensive than PTP, that need to be mapped into
不同的网络层级中。
different network hierarchies.
例如，如果你有高带宽，你应该优先选择降维操作。
For example, if you have high bandwidth, you should prefer to reduce.
如果你的带宽较低，你应该避免使用降维操作。
And if you have low bandwidth, you should prefer to use you should avoid radius.
你应该优先使用点对点通信。
You should prefer using PTP.
在下一节课中，我将介绍这个用于通信的原语
In the next lecture, I'm going to introduce this to communicating
以确保我们理解其背后的数学原理。谢谢。
primitives to make sure we understand the mathematics behind it. Thank you.